<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Anno quinto et sexto Eduardi Sexti Actes made in the session of this present parlament, holden vpo[n] prorogacion at Westminster, the. xxiii. daie of Ianuarie, in the fiueth yere of the reigne of our moste drad souereigne Lorde, Edward the. VI. by the grace of God, kyng of Englande, Fraunce, and Irelande, defendour of the faith, and of the Churche of Englande and Irelande, in yearth [sic] the supreme hed: and there continued and kept to the. xv. daie of Aprill, in the vi. yere of the reigne of our saied souereigne lorde, as foloweth</title>
            <title>Laws, etc.</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1547-1553 : Edward VI)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 202KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 35 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A74034</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99898995</idno>
  <idno type="VID">150874</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240870564</idno>
  <idno type="STC">STC 9433</idno>
  <idno type="STC">ESTC S124832</idno>
  
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99898995e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A74034)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 150874)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1984:37)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Anno quinto et sexto Eduardi Sexti Actes made in the session of this present parlament, holden vpo[n] prorogacion at Westminster, the. xxiii. daie of Ianuarie, in the fiueth yere of the reigne of our moste drad souereigne Lorde, Edward the. VI. by the grace of God, kyng of Englande, Fraunce, and Irelande, defendour of the faith, and of the Churche of Englande and Irelande, in yearth [sic] the supreme hed: and there continued and kept to the. xv. daie of Aprill, in the vi. yere of the reigne of our saied souereigne lorde, as foloweth</title>
                  <title>Laws, etc.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1547-1553 : Edward VI)</author>
                  <author>Edward VI, King of England, 1537-1553.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>xxxiij leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Richardus Graftonus typographus Regius excudebat,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>mense Aprili. 1552.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank--STC.</note>
                  <note>In this edition, the 'D' of signature D2 is under 'no' of 'dishonour'--STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-E⁶ F⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library, Cambridge, England.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Law --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1547-1553 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="illustrated_title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:150874:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>top: a king or Edward VI seated in the court of parliament, with male figures on both sides; left and right: classical columns or pillars; bottom: two angels or cherubs kneeling beside a tree growing from a barrel</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>ANNO QVINTO ET SEXTO EDVARDI <hi>SEXTI.</hi> ❧ <hi>ACTES</hi> made in the Session of this present parlament, holden vpō proro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gacion at Westminster, the .xxiii. daie of Ianuarie, in the fiueth yere of the reigne of our moste drad souereigne Lorde, Edward the .<hi>VI.</hi> by the grace of God, kyng of Englande, Fraunce, and Irelande, defendour of the faith, and of the Churche of Englande and Irelande, in yearth the supreme hed: and there continued and kept to the .xv. daie of Aprill, in the <hi>VI.</hi> yere of the reigne of our saied souerei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gne lorde, as foloweth</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:150874:2"/>
            <head>❧ THE <hi>Table.</hi> ❧</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N primis, an acte for the vniformitie of common praier, and admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stracion of the Sacramentes. Chapiter .i.</item>
               <item>An acte for the prouision and relief of the poore. Chapiter .ij.</item>
               <item>An acte for the kepyng of holy daies, and fastyng daies. Chapiter .iij.</item>
               <item>An acte against fyghtyng and quarelyng in churches, and churche-yardes. Chapiter .iiij.</item>
               <item>An acte for the maintenaunce of Tillage, and encreace of corne. Chapiter .v.</item>
               <item>An acte for the true makyng of wollen cloth. Chapiter .vi.</item>
               <item>An acte limityng the tymes for buyeng and sellyng of wolles. Chapiter .vij.</item>
               <item>An act limiting what persones shal weaue or make brode wollē cloth. Chap .viij.</item>
               <item>An acte that no man robbyng any house, Bouthe, or Lent, shalbe admitted to the benefite of his clergie. Chapiter .ix.</item>
               <item>An acte to take away the benefite of clergie, from such as robbe in one shiere, and flie into another. Chapiter .x.</item>
               <item>An acte for the punishement of diuerse treasons. Chapiter .xi.</item>
               <item>An acte for the declaracion of a statute, made for the mariage of priestes, and for the legitimacion of their children. Chapiter .xij.</item>
               <item>An acte for the declaracion of a statute made in the .xxxi. yere of kyng Henry the eyght, touchyng religious persones. Chapiter .xiij</item>
               <item>An acte against regratours, forestallers, and engrossers. Chapiter .xiiij.</item>
               <item>An acte against regratours of tanned lether. Chapiter .xv.</item>
               <item>An acte against buyeng and sellyng of offices. Chapiter .xvi.</item>
               <item>An acte for the continuaunce of certeyne statutes. Chapiter .xvij.</item>
               <item>An acte repealyng a statute made in the fourth yere of Kyng Henry the seuenth, against the bryngyng in of wyne, and woad, in straunge botomes. Chapiter .xviij.</item>
               <item>An acte touchyng the exchaunge of golde and siluer. Chapiter .xix.</item>
               <item>An acte against vsury. Chapiter .xx.</item>
               <item>An acte for Tinckers and Pedlers. Chapiter .xxi.</item>
               <item>An acte for the puttyng downe of Gygge milles. Chapiter .xxij.</item>
               <item>An acte for the true stuffing of fetherbeddes, mattresses &amp; quissheons. Chap .xxiij.</item>
               <item>An acte for the makyng of hattes, dornyckes, and couerlectes at Norwiche, and in the countie of Northfolcke. Chapiter .xxiiij.</item>
               <item>An acte for kepers of Alehouses, to be bounde by recognisaunce. Chapiter .xxv.</item>
               <item>An acte for writtes vpon proclamacions and exigentes, to be curraunt within the countie palantine of lancaster. Chapiter .xxvi.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <pb n="ij" facs="tcp:150874:2"/>
            <head>¶ The first Chapiter. ¶ An acte, for the vniformitie of common praier, and administra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of the Sacramentes.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here there hath been a verie Godly order sette furthe, by aucthoritie of Parlament, for common praier, and administracion of the Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, to be vsed in the mother tongue, within this Churche of Englande, agreable to the woorde of God, and the primatiue Churche, verie com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable to al good people, desiryng to liue in christian conuersacion, and moste profitable to the state of this realme, vpon the whiche, the mercie, fauoure, and blessyng of almightie God, is in no wise so redily, and plenteously powred, as by common praiers, due vsyng of the Sacramentes, and often Preachyng of the Gospell, with the deuocion of the hearers. And yet this notwithstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng, a greate nomber of people, in diuerse partes of this realme, fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowyng their awne sensualitie, and liuyng either without knowlege, or due feare of God, do wilfully and dampnably before almightie god abstein, and refuse to come to their Parishe Churches, and other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, where common praier, administracion of the Sacramentes, and Preachyng of the woorde of God is vsed, vpon the Sondaies, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther daies, ordeined to be holy daies.</p>
            <p>For reformacion hereof, bee it enacted, by the Kyng our souereigne lorde, with the assent of the lordes, and commons, in this present Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lament assembled, and by the aucthoritie of thesame, that from, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the feast of all Sainctes next commyng, all and euery persone, and persones, enhabityng within this realme, or any other the kynges ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iesties dominions, shall diligently, and faithfully, hauyng no lawfull or reasonable excuse to be absent, endeuour themselfes to resort to their Parishe Churche, or Chapell accustomed, or vpon reasonable let ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, to some vsuall place, where cōmon praier, and suche seruice of God shalbe vsed, in suche tyme of let, vpon euery Sondaie, and other daies ordeined, and vsed to be kepte, as holy daies, and then, and there to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide orderly, and soberly, duryng the tyme of the common praier, prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chynges, or other seruice of God, there to be vsed and ministered, vpon pain of punishement, by the Censures of the Churche.</p>
            <p>And for the due execucion hereof, the Kynges moste excellent Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iestie,
<pb facs="tcp:150874:3"/> the lordes temporall, and all the commones in this present Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lament assembled, doth in Goddes name earnestly require, and charge all the Archebishoppes, Bishoppes, and other Ordinaries, that thei shall endeuour theimselfes, to the vttermoste of their knowleges, that the due and true execucion hereof maie be had, throughout their Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesses and charges, as thei will answere before God, for suche euilles and plagues, wherewith almightie God, maie iustly punishe his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, for necglectyng this good and wholesome lawe.</p>
            <p>And for their aucthoritie in this behalfe, be it further likewise ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, by the aucthoritie aforesaid, that all, and singuler, thesame Arche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bishoppes, Bishoppes, and all other their officers exercisyng Ecclesia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sticall Iurisdiccion, aswell in place exempt, as not exempt, within their diocesses, shall haue full power and aucthoritie by this acte, to reforme correct, and punishe by Censures of the Churche, all and singuler per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sones whiche shall offende within any their iurisdiccions, or Diocesses after thesaied feast of all Sainctes, nexte commyng, against this Acte and statute, any other Lawe, statute, preuilege, libertie, or prouision, heretofore made, had, or suffered, to the contrary, notwithstandyng.</p>
            <p>And because there hath arisen, in the vse and exercise of the foresaid common seruice in the Churche, heretofore set furthe, diuerse doubtes for the fashion and maner of the ministracion of thesame, rather by the curiositie of the minister, and mistakers, then of any other worthy cause therfore, aswell for the more plain and manifest explanacion hereof, as for the more perfeccion of thesaid order of common seruice, in some pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces where it is necessary to make thesame praier and fashion of seruice more earnest and fitte, to stirre christian people to the true honouryng of almightie God: The Kynges moste excellent maiestie, with thassent of the lordes and commons in this present Parlament assembled, and by the aucthoritie of thesame, hath caused the foresaied order of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon seruice, entituled the Boke of common praier, to be faithfully and Godly perused, explaned, and made fully perfect, and by the foresaied aucthoritie, hath annexed and ioyned it, so explaned and perfected to this present statute, addyng also a fourme and maner of makyng, and consecratyng of Archebishoppes, Bishoppes, Priestes, and Deacons, to be of like force, aucthoritie, and value, as thesame like foresaid boke entituled the Boke of common praier was before, and to be accepted, receiued, vsed, and estemed, in like sorte and maner, and with thesame clauses of prouisions and excepcions to all ententes, construccions, and purposes, as by the Acte of Parlament, made in the second yere of the kynges Maiesties reigne, was ordeined, limited, expressed, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poyncted, for the vniformitie of seruice, and administracion of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentes, throughout the Realme, vpon suche seuerall paines, as in thesaied Acte of Parlament is expressed. And thesaied former Acte, to stand in full force and strength, to all ententes, and construccions, and
<pb n="iij" facs="tcp:150874:3"/> to be applied, practised, and put in vre, to, and for thestablishyng of the boke of common praier, now explaned, and hereunto annexed, and also thesaied fourme of makyng of Archebishoppes, Bishoppes, Priestes, and Deacons, hereunto annexed, as it was for the former boke.</p>
            <p>And by thaucthoritie aforesaid it is now further enacted, that if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny maner of persone, or persones, enhabityng and beyng, within this realme, or any other the kynges maiesties dominiōs, shall after thesaid feast of al Sainctes, willyngly, and wittyngly, heare, and be present at any other maner, or forme, of common praier, of administracion of the Sacramentes of makyng of ministers in the churches, or of any other rites, conteined in the boke annexed to this acte, then is mencioned, and set furthe in thesaied boke, or that is contrary to the fourme of sondrie prouisions, and excepcions, conteined in the foresaied former statute, and shalbee thereof conuicted, accordyng to the lawes of this realme, before the Iustices of Assise, Iustices of Dyer and determiner, Iusti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Peace in their Sessions, or any of them, by the verdict of twelue men, or by his, or their awne confession, or otherwise, shall for the firste offence suffer enprisonment, for sixe monethes, without baile, or main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prise, and for the second offence, beyng likewise conuicted, as is aboue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saied, emprisonment for one whole yere, and for the third offence, in like maner emprisonmēt, duryng his or their lifes. And for the more know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege to be geuen hereof, and better obseruacion of this lawe: be it enac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the aucthoritie aforesaied, that all, and synguler Curates, shall vpon one Sondaie euery quarter of the yere, duryng one whole yere next folowyng the foresaied feast of all Sainctes next commyng, rede this present acte in the Churche, at the tyme of the moste assembly, and likewise once in euery yere folowyng, at thesame tyme, declaryng vnto the people, by the aucthoritie of the scripture, how the mercy and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of God, hath in all ages bene shewed to his people, in their necessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and extremities, by meanes of hartie and faithfull praiers, made to almightie God, especially where people bee gathered together with one faithe and mynd, to offer vp their hartes by praier, as the best Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices that christian men can yeld.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ The .ij. Chapiter. ¶ An acte, for the prouision and relief of the poore.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O the entent, that valiaunt beggers, idle, and loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryng persones, maie be auoyded, and the impotent feble, and lame, prouided for, which are poore in ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry deede: Be it enacted by the Kyng our souereigne Lorde, with the assent of the Lordes, Spirituall and Temporall, and the Commons in this present Parlament assembled, and by aucthoritie of the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>same, that aswel the statute, made in the .xxij. yere of the late Kyng, of famous memorie, Kyng Henry the eight, as also the
<pb facs="tcp:150874:4"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#oxf" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="iij" facs="tcp:150874:4"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#oxf" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:150874:5"/> statute, made in the third, and fourthe yere of the reigne of the kynges maiestie that now is, concernyng beggers, vagabondes, and idle per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sones, and euery article, clause, braunche, sentence, and other thynges, conteined in theim, and in euery of them (other then suche thynges, as shalbe by this present acte ordeined, and prouided for) shall stande, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main, and be in their full force, and effect, and shalbe from hencefurthe iustly, and truely, put in execucion, accordyng to the true meanyng of thesaied seuerall statutes, and euery of them.</p>
            <p>And further, be it enacted by the aucthoritie aforesaied, that yerely, one holy daie in Whiteson weke, in euery citee, borough, and toune cor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>porate the Maior, Bailifes, or other hed officers, for the tyme beeyng: and in euery other Parishe or the countrey, the Persone, Vicar, or Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, and the Churchewardeines (hauyng in a regester, or boke, aswell all the names of thenhabitātes, and housholders, as also the names, of al suche impotent, aged, and nedy persones, as beyng within their citee Borough toune corporate, or Parishe, are not able to liue of themsel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fes, nor with their awne labor,) shall openly in the Churche, and quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, after diuine seruice, call thesaid housholders, and enhabitauntes to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gether. Emong whom, the Maior, and to of his brethren, in euery citee, the Bailifes, or other hed officers, in Boroughes, and tounes Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, the Persone, Vicare, or Curate, and Churchewardeins, in euery o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Parishe: shall electe, nominate, and appoynct yerely, two able per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sones or mo, to be gatherers, and collectours of the charitable almose of all the residue of the people, for the relief of the poore. Whiche Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectours, the Sondaie next after their eleccion, (or the Sondaie folow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng, if nede require) when the people is at the churche, and hath heard Gods holy worde, shall gently aske, and demaunde of euery man, and woman, what thei of their charitie, wilbe contented to geue wekely, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the relief of the poore. And thesame to be written, in thesaid regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster, or boke. And thesaid gatherers, so beyng elected, and chosen, shall iustly gather, and truely distribute thesame charitable almose wekely (by themselues, or their assignes) to thesaid poore, &amp; impotent persones of thesaied citees, boroughes, tounes corporate, or Parishes without fraude, or couin, fauour, or affecciō. And after suche sort, that the more impotent, maie haue the more helpe: and suche, as can get part of their liuyng, to haue the lesse. And by the discrecion of the collectours, to bee put in suche labour as thei be fitte, and able to dooe, but none to go, or sitte openly a beggyng-vpon pam limited in the aforesaied statutes.</p>
            <p>Be it also enacted, by the aucthoritie aforesaied, that no persone, or persones, so elected, nominated, and appoyncted to be gatherer or ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therers, as is aforesaid, shall refuse thesaied office, but shall iustly, and truely execute thesame by the space of one whole yere next ensuyng, v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pō pain of forfeictyng .xx. s̄. to the almose boxe of the poore to be leuied by the churchwardeins, where thei, or he dwelleth, of the goodes of the
<pb n="iiij" facs="tcp:150874:5"/> saied gatherer, or gatherers, so refusyng, by distresse.</p>
            <p>And further, be it enacted by the aucthoritie aforesaid, that thesaid gatherers, or collectours, shall make their iust accompte quarterly, to the Maior of the citee, Bailifes, or hedde Officers of the Borough, or toune corporate: and in euery Parishe of the countrey, to the Persone, Vicar, or Curate, and Churchewardeins of the Parishe. At whiche ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt, suche of the Parishe, as will, maie be present. And when thei go out of their office, thei shall deliuer, or cause to be deliuered, furthewith vpon thende of their accomptes, al suche surplusage of money, as then shall remain of their colleccion vndistributed, to be put in the common chest of the churche, or in some other saufe place, to the vse of the poore, at the ouer sight, and discrecion of thesaied Maior, or other the officers before mencioned. And if thesaid collectours, or any of them, do refuse to make their saied accompt, within eight daies: then the Bishop of the Dioces, or Ordinarie, shall haue aucthoritie, by vertue of this acte, to compell thesaied persone, or persones, by Censures of the Churche, to make their saied accomptes, before suche persones, as thesaied Bishop or Ordinarie, shall appoyncte.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted, by the aucthoritie aforesaied, that if any<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>persone, or persons, beyng able to further this charitable worke, do ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinately and frowardly, refuse to geue towardes the help of the poore, or doo wilfully discourage other, from so charitable a deede: The Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sone Vicar, or Curate, and Churchewardeins, of the Parishe where he dwelleth, shall gently exhorte hym, or theim, towardes the relief of the poore. And if he, or thei, wil not so be perswaded, then vpō the certificat of the Persone, Vicar, or Curate of the Parishe, to the Bishoppe of the Dioces, thesame Bishoppe shall sende for hym, or them, to induce, and perswade hym, or theim, by charitable waies, and meanes. And so ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordyng to his discrecion, to take order for the reformacion hereof.</p>
            <p>And for the better maintenaunce of this charitable worke, it is or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deined, and established, by aucthoritie aforesaied, that where as the late kyng, of famous memorie, Kyng Henry the eight, by his seuerall erec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions and foundacions, hath ordeined and appoincted, any some, or so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes of money, to thuse of the poore (not beyng taken awaie, otherwise by acte of Parlament) whether thesame be in any Cathedrall churche, College, or els where: the Bishoppe of the Dioces, for the tyme beyng, shall from tyme to tyme, examine, how, and after what maner, thesaied money is bestowed, and call to accompt the parties, whiche retain the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saied money, so that it maie appere, that thesame is distributed to the poore, accordyng to the kynges maiesties foundacion.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwaies, and be it further enacted, by the aucthoritie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresaied, that this present Acte, nor any thyng therein conteined, shall extende, or bee preiudiciall vnto the Maior, Shirefes, and Citezeins, of the citee of Chester, for, or concernyng any gift, or graunt, of any an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuitie,
<pb facs="tcp:150874:6"/> or yerely rent, heretofore made, geuen, or graūted by the kynges maiestie that now is, vnto thesaid Maior, Shiereues, and citezeins, of thesaied citee, goyng out of any manours, landes, tenementes, and he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reditamentes, of the Cathedrall churche of Christ, and our Lady, with in the citee of Chester, but that thesame Maior, Shiereues, and cite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zeins, shall, and maie, from hencefurthe, receiue, vse, and employe, the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>same annuities, yerely rentes, or profectes, to suche vses, and ententes, and accordyng to thesaid gift of our saied souereigne Lorde the Kyng any thyng in this present acte to the contrary, notwithstandyng. This acte to endure to the ende of the first Session, of the next Parlament.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ The .iii. Chapiter. ¶ An acte, for the kepyng of holy daies, and fastyng daies.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Orasmuche as at all tymes men be not so mindful to laude and praise God, so redy to resort and heare Gods holy worde, and to come to the holy commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and other laudable rites, whiche are to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serued in euery Christian congregacion, as their bounden dutie doth require: therfore to call men to remembraunce of their dutie, and to helpe their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmitie, it hath been wholesomely prouided, that there should be some certain tymes and daies appoyncted, wherein the christians should cease from all other kynd of labours, and should ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply themselfes onely, and wholy, vnto the aforesaied holy workes, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly perteinyng vnto true religion. That is, to heare, to learne, and to remember almightie Gods greate benefites, his manifold mercies, his inestimable gracious goodnes, so plenteously powred vpō al his crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and that of his infinite, and vnspeakeable goodnes, without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny mannes deserte. And in remembraunce hereof, to render vnto hym, moste high and hartie thankes, with praiers and supplicacions, for the relief of all oure daiely necessities. And because these bee the chief and principall workes, wherein man is commaunded to worship God, and do properly pertain vnto the first table: therfore as these woorkes, are bothe moste commonly, and also maie well bee called Gods seruice, so the tymes appoyncted specially for thesame, are called holy daies. Not for the matter and nature, either of the tyme, or daie, nor for any of the sainctes sakes, whose memories are had on those daies (for so al daies and tymes considered are Gods creatures, and all of like holines) but for the nature and condicion of those Godly and holy workes, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with onely God is to be honoured, and the congregacion to be edified, whereunto suche tymes and daies, are sanctified and hallowed. That is to saie, separated frō all prophane vses, and dedicated and appoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, not vnto any sainct or creature, but onely vnto God, and his true worship Neither is it to be thought, that there is any certaine tyme or
<pb n="v" facs="tcp:150874:6"/> definite nomber of daies, prescribed in holy scripture, but that the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynctement, bothe of the tyme, and also of the nomber of the daies, is left by thaucthoritie of Gods worde, to the libertie of Christes churche to be determined and assigned orderly in euery countrey, by the discre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of the rulers and ministers therof, as thei shall iudge moste expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient to the true settyng furthe of Goddes glory, and the edificacion of their people. Be it therefore enacted, by the kyng our souereigne lorde, with thassent of the lordes spirituall and temporall, and the commons in this present Parlament assembled, and by thaucthoritie of thesame, that all the daies hereafter mencioned, shalbe kept, and commaunded, to be kept holy daies, and none other. That is to saie, all Sondaies in the yere, the daies of the feastes of the Circumcision of our lorde Iesus Christ. Of the Epiphanie. Of the Purificacion of the blessed Virgin. Of S. Mathie the Apostle. Of the Annunciacion of the blessed virgin Of sainct Marke the Euangelist. Of sainct Philip and Iacob the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles. Of the Ascencion of our lorde Iesus Christ. Of the Natiuitie of sainct Ihon Baptist. Of sainct Peter the Apostle. Of sainct Iames the Apostle. Of saincte Bartholomewe the Apostle. Of saincte Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thewe the Apostle. Of sainct Michaell tharchaungel. Of sainct Luke the Euangelist. Of sainct Simon and Iude the Apostles. Of all sain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctes Of sainct Andrewe the Apostle. Of saincte Thomas the Apostle. Of the Natiuitie of our Lorde. Of saincte Stephen the Martire. Of saincte Ihon the Euangelist. Of the holy Innocentes. Monedaie, and Twesdaie in Easter weke. And Monedaie and Twesdaie in White<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son weke And that none other daie shalbe kept, and commaunded to be kept holy daie, or to abstein from lawfull bodily labour.</p>
            <p>And it is also enacted, by the aucthoritie aforesaid, that euery euen or daie, next goyng before any of the aforesaied daies, of the feastes of the Natiuitie of our Lorde, of Easter, of the Ascencion of our Lorde, Pentecost, of the Purificacion, and the Annunciacion of the aforesaid blessed virgin, of all Sainctes, and of all of thesaid feastes of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles (other then of sainct Ihon the Euāgelist, and Philip and Iacob) shalbe fasted, and commaunded so to be kepte, and obserued, and that none other euen, or daie, shalbe commaunded to be fasted.</p>
            <p>And it is enacted, by the aucthoritie aboue saied, that it shalbe law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to all Archebishoppes, and Bishoppes, in their Diocesses, and to all other hauyng Ecclesiasticall, or Spirituall iurisdiccion, to enquire of euery persone, that shall offende in the premisses, and to punish eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry suche offendor, by the Censures of the Churche, and to enioyne him, or them, suche penaunce, as shalbe to the Spirituall Iudge, by his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>screcion thought mete, and conuenient.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwaies, that this Acte, or any thyng therein conteined, shall not extende to abrogate, or take awaie, the abstinence from fleshe, in Lent, or on Fridaies, and Saturdaies, or any other daie, whiche is
<pb facs="tcp:150874:7"/> alredy appoyncted so to be kepte, by vertue of an Acte, made, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided, in the third yere of the reigne of our souereigne Lorde the kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges maiestie that now is, sauyng onely of those euens, or daies, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the holy daie next folowyng is abrogated by this statute. Any thing aboue mencioned to the contrary in any wise, notwithstandyng.</p>
            <p>Prouided also, and it is enacted by the aucthoritie aforesaied, that when, and so often, as it shall chaunce any of thesaid feastes (the euens whereof be by this statute commaunded to bee obserued, and kepte fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>styng daie) dooe fall vpon the Monedaie: that then, as it hath alwaies been heretofore accustomably vsed, so hereafter the Saturdaie, then nexte goyng before any suche feast, or holy daie, and not the Sondaie, shalbe commaunded to be fasted, for the euen of any suche feast, or ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly daie. Any thyng in this statute, before mencioned or declared, to the contrary in any wise, notwithstandyng.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwaies, and it is enacted by the aucthoritie aforesaied, that it shalbe lawfull to euery husbandman, labourer, Fisherman, and and to all, and euery other persone, and persones, of what estate, degree or condicion he, or thei be, vpon the holy daies aforesaied, in haruest, or at any other tymes in the yere, when necessitie shall require, to labour, ride, fishe, or worke any kind of worke, at their free willes and pleasure Any thyng in this acte to the contrary, in any wise notwithstandyng.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwaies, and be it enacted, by the aucthoritie aforesaied, that it shalbe lawfull to the knightes, of the right honourable order of the Garter, and to euery of them, to kepe, and celebrate solempnely, the feast of their order (commonly called sainct Georges feast) yerely from hencefurthe, the .xxii. xxiii. and .xxiiii. daies of Aprill, and at suche other tyme, and tymes, as yerely shalbe thought conuenient by the Kynges highnes, his heires and successors, and thesaid knightes of thesaid ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable order, or any of them now beyng, or hereafter to be. Any thyng in this acte heretofore mencioned to the contrary, notwithstandyng.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ The .iiii. Chapiter. ¶ An acte, against fightyng, and quarellyng, in Churches, and Churche yardes.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or asmuche as of late, diuerse and many outragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and barbarous behauors &amp; actes, haue been vsed, and committed by diuerse vngodly, and irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious persons, by quarellyng, braulyng, fraiyng and fightyng, openly in Churches, and Churche yardes: therfore it is enacted by the kyng our so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uereigne lorde, with the assent of the lordes spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual and temporal, &amp; the commons in this present Parlament assembled, and by thaucthoritie of thesame, that if any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sone whatsoeuer, shall at any tyme after the first daie of Maie next cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myng,
<pb n="vi" facs="tcp:150874:7"/> by woordes onely, querell, chide, or brawle in any Churche, or Churche yarde, that then it shalbee lawfull vnto the Ordinarie of the place, where thesame offence shalbe doen, and proued by twoo lawfull witnesses, to suspende euery persone so offendyng. That is to saie, if he be a laye man, <hi>ab ingressu Ecclesiae,</hi> and if he be a clerke, from the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stracion of his office, for so long tyme as thesaied Ordenarie shall by his discrecion thynke mete, and conuenient, accordyng to the faulte.</p>
            <p>And further it is enacted, by the aucthoritie aforesaied, that if any persone, or persones, after thesaied first daie of Maie, shall smite, or lay any violent handes vpon any other, either in any Churche, or Churche yarde: That then, <hi>Ipso facto,</hi> euery persone so offendyng, shalbe demed excommunicate, and bee excluded from the felowship and company of Christes congregacion.</p>
            <p>And also it is enacted by the aucthoritie aforesaied, that if any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sone, after thesaied first daie of Maie, shall maliciously strike any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sone, with any weapon, in any Churche, or Churche yarde, or after thesame firste daie of Maie, shall drawe any weapon, in any Chuche, or Churche yarde, to the entent to strike another with thesame weapon: That then euery persone so offendyng, and therof beyng conuicted by verdict of twelue menne, or by his awne confession, or by twoo lawfull witnesses, before the Iustices of Assise, Iustices of Dyer and determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, or Iustices of Peace, in their Sessions, by force of this Acte, shal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be adiudged by thesame Iustices, before whom suche person, shalbe so conuicted, to haue one of his eares cutte of. And if the persone, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sones, so offendyng, haue none eares, wherby thei should receiue suche punishment, as is afore declared: that then he, or thei, to be marked and burned in the cheke, with an hotte yron hauyng this letter. <hi>F.</hi> vhereby he, or thei, maie be knowen, and taken, for fraye makers and fighters, and besides that, euery suche persone, to be, and stande, <hi>Ipso facto,</hi> exco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated, as is aforesaied.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ The .v. Chapiter. ¶ An Acte, for the maintenaunce of Tillage, and encrease of corne.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>OR the better maintenaunce of Tillage, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease of Corne, to bee had within this Realme, whiche of late tyme, been muche decayed, by suche as haue conuerted landes vsually put in Tillage to Pasture: Bee it enacted by the Kyng our soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigne Lorde, with the assent of the Lordes and Commons, in this present Parlament assembled, and by thaucthoritie of thesame, that there shalbe yerely, after the feast of the Annunciacion of our Lady, whiche shalbe in the yere of our Lorde God, a thousande, fiue hundred, fiftie and thre
<pb facs="tcp:150874:8"/> asmuche lande, or more, put wholy in Tillage, and vsed, and sowen, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordyng to the custome of the countrey, and nature of the ground, and so shalbe continued and vsed for Tillage, and Sowen for euer, by the owners, Fermours, or occupiers therof, in euery Toune, Parishe, Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage, and Hammelet, within the Realme of Englande, and Wales: as was, or hath been put in Tillage, in any one yere, and so kepte in Til<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage, by the space of .iiii. yeres, any tyme sence the first yere of the reigne of Kyng Henry theight, vpon pain to forfeict to the kyng, and his hei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, for euery acre not put in Tillage, vsed and occupied, accordyng to the fourme, and effecte, of this present Acte v. s̄. for euery yere so offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng. And for the better execucion of this acte: be it enacted by the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cthoritie aforesaid, that our saied souereigne lorde the kyng, his heires and successours, at his and their will, and pleasure, from tyme, to tyme maie direct his, and their seuerall Commission, and Commissions, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the greate Seale of Englande, to suche persones, as it shall please theim. And that thesame Commissioners, or foure of theim at the least, shall haue power and aucthoritie, by vertue of this acte, and of thesaid Commission, to enquire, searche, and trie, by thothes of twelue lawfull and indifferent persones, or more, in euery Hundred, Rape, or Wapen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take, suche as maie dispende yerely .xl. s̄. of Frehold: what landes, and Tenementes, in euery Toune, Parishe, Village, or Hammelet, within the limites of their charge (haue against the fourme and effecte, of this present acte, and statute) at any tyme, or tymes, sence thesaied first yere of the reigne, of kyng Henry theight, been conuerted, and turned from Tillage, to Pasture, and so liyng conuerted, and turned, from Tillage to Pasture, and is now, or hereafter so shalbe continued, and occupied in Pasture. And that thesaid twelue persones, or more, vpō their othes shall make true and lawfull presentment, and certificate, aswell of all, and synguler, the premisses, as of the names, or sirenames, of the owe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, Fermours, and occupiers of thesame, in writyng vnder their sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, to thesaied Commissioners, at suche daie, tyme, and place, as shalbe limited to theim, by thesaied Commissioners. And that thesaeid Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missioners, after suche presentmentes therof, had, and made, shall cause thesame presentmentes, to be engrossed in Parchement, endented, and sealed with their seales, wherof the one part therof, shalbe deliuered to the foreman of the Iurie, and the other part therof, shalbe certefied in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the kynges Court of Chauncerie, within twoo monethes, next after suche presentment, so had and made. And that from thencefurthe, the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said presentmentes, with conuenient spede shalbe certefied, and streted out, and from, thesaied Court of Chauncerie into the Court of the Es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheaquer, there to remain of Record, emong the Kynges Maiesties re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordes of thesame Court of the Escheaquer, to the entent that this sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute shalbe the more diligently, and indifferently, put in the execucion, accordyng to the true meanyng therof.</p>
            <pb n="vij" facs="tcp:150874:8"/>
            <p>And be it further enacted by the aucthoritie aforesaid, that suche commissioners as shal hereafter be aucthorised by vertue of the Kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges commission, to put this Acte in execution, shall before suche tyme as he, or thei, shal sitte vpon thesame commission, take a corporal othe before the Lorde Chauncellour of Englande, or the Lord keper of the great Seale for the tyme beyng, or before suche other persone, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, as shall haue aucthoritie from the Lorde Chauncellour of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande, or the keper of the great Seale for the tyme beyng, by <hi>Dedimus potestatem,</hi> to receiue, and take his, or their othes, truely, faithfully, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differently, and iustly, accordyng to the vttermost of his, or their wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, learnynges and connynges to endeuoure them selues, for, and to the true execution of this statute, and of al, and euery thyng, conteined in the same, for the better maintenaunce of tillage, &amp; encrease of corne to be had, accordyng to the true meanyng of this Acte.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted, by thaucthoritie aforesaid, that thesaid commissioners, or two of them at the leaste, shall haue aucthoritie, and power, to directe their precepte to the Shieriefe of the countie, beyng within the limites of their commission, to warne suche, and as many honest men of his Bailiwicke as is aforesaid, by whom the truth may best be knowen, to enquire, and true presentment make, of all, and eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the premisses, and to sette suche reasonable fynes, yssues, and amer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciamentes, vpon suche persones, as shall make defaulte of their appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances, or makyng their apparances, shall neglecte to do their duties, in, and about the execution of the premisses, as to the same commissio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, or fowre of them, shalbe by their discretions thought mete, and conuenient, so that the same fine, or amerciament, for any one defaulte excede not the somme of xx. s̄. And that the same fynes, yssues, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merciamentes, so by them taxed, and sette, shalbe yerely, well, and true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly streated, into thesaid court of theschequier, and there to be leuied to the Kynges vse, as other fynes, and amerciamentes, haue bene there accustomed and vsed to be leuied.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwaies, and be it enacted by thaucthoritie aforesaid, that the puttyng of any landes, or tenementes hereafter, from pasture, to tillage, accordyng to the forme and effecte of this Acte, shall not in any wyse extende, to be any cause of breache, or forfeicture of any bonde, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenaunt, paiment, or condicion, made, or hereafter to be made, betwene any person, or persons, whiche in any wyse is, or shalbe repugnaunt, or contrariant to this Acte.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwaies, and it is enacted by thaucthoritie aforesaid, that this Acte, ne any thyng therin conteined, shall not in any wyse, extende to any lande, conuerted, or to be cōuerted into pasture, that shalbe kept without fraude, or couine, onely for the maintenaunce of the houses &amp; hospitalitie, of any person, or persones, nor to any land, that commonly or vsually, hath lien to pasture, by the space of .xl. yeres laste past, nor
<pb facs="tcp:150874:9"/> to any wast groundes, or heithes, nor to any common downes, fennes, moores, or marisshes, whiche haue not bene comonly, and vsually, for the most parte sowen, or put in tillage, within .xl. yeres last past, nor to any land now beyng lawful warren, or now vsed and kept for Conies, nor to any grounde stubbed, or wonne, from wood, busshes, broome, or fyrres, into the kynde of pasture, nor to any lande now enclosed in any parke, commonly vsed with dere, and that without fraude, or couine, hath bene vsed for any parke, within .iiij. yeres, last before this present session of the Parlament, nor to any salte marsshes, nor to any mars<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shes that commonly within ten yeres hath bene ones surrounded, or ouer flowen with water, nor to any grounde enclosed by the licence of our souereigne Lorde the Kyng, or any of his noble progenitours, nor to any orcharde, gardein, poole, or ponde yarde, nor to any medowe grounde yerely mowen, or to be mowen for haye, nor to any lande sette or to be sette, with saffron, or with hoppes, nor to any lande sowen, or to be sowen, with hempe, flaxe. woade, or madder, nor to any lande with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out fraude, or couine, sowen, or to be sowē with acornes, or set, or to be sette with wood, duryng suche tymes as thesame shalbe vsed, or put to the vses and ententes before specified.</p>
            <p>Prouided also, and be it further enacted by thaucthoritie aforesaid, that this Acte, nor any thyng therin conteined, shal in any wise extende or be preiudiciall, or hurtfull to any person, or persons, whiche at any tyme heretofore hath conuerted, or at any tyme, or times, hereafter shal conuerte any arable lande, to pastute, in any paroche, towne, village, hammelet, or other place, or places, of this Realme, for the whiche suche person, or persons, hath already, or within one yere aftre the feast of ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster nexte commyng, or within one yere nexte after any suche enquisiciō hereafter to be founde, after suche conuertyng of arable grounde, into pasture, hath, or shall turne, or conuert to tillage, and arable grounde, asmuche pasture grounde, or lease within thesame paroche, towne, vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage, or hammelet, or within any of them, where any suche land so hath bene, or hereafter shalbe conuerted, from tillage, to pasture, and do suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the same lande, so turned from pasture to tillage, so to continue in tillage, and be arable without turnyng the same to pasture againe, so longe as the landes turned to pasture, as aforesaid, shalbe vsed in pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sture. Any thyng in this present Acte conteined to the contrary hereof, in any wyse, notwithstandyng.</p>
            <p>And it is further enacted by thaucthoritie aforesaid, that as well all commissioners, Iustices of Assise, Iustices of Oyer and determiner, as Iustices of peace in their sessions, and none other, shall haue full power, and aucthoritie, to enquire of the premisses, and shal certifie al presentmentes that shalbe had before them, into the court of chaunce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and from thence to be streated in conuenient tyme, into the Kynges court of theschequier, and that the partie greued, if he wille, may haue,
<pb n="xi" facs="tcp:150874:9"/> and tende his trauerse, accordyng to the lawes of this Realme, in the same court, whether thesaid landes, or tenementes, so founden, by any suche enquisition, be holden of the kyng immediately, or not.</p>
            <p>Prouided also, and be it enacted by thaucthoritie aforsaid, that this acte, nor any thyng therin conteined, shal, or may, in any wise extende, to geue any aucthoritie to any shierefe, vndershierefe, or any their offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer, bailife, or minister, to enfringe, breake, or entre, into any liberty, or liberties, for the execution of any precept, or other processe, whiche shal be hereafter to him, or them, awarded by thaucthoritie, and vertue of thys acte, otherwyse then he, or they, might haue done, before the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng of thesame. Any thing herin conteined to the contrary in any wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se, notwithstandyng.</p>
            <p>Prouided also and be it further enacted by thaucthoritie aforesaid, that if any persons, or persone offendyng this acte, be at any time here after empeched, or sued by force of this acte, for any offence, or offences committed, or done, or to be committed, or done, contrary to thys acte that thē the partie offendyng so sued, shal not be empeched, by the king our souereigne lorde, or by any other, for thesame offence, by vertue of any lawe, acte, or actes, statute, or statutes, hertofore had, or made, for the reformation of any the articles, or braunches, cōteined in this act, Any thyng in this acte, or any other acte, or actes, had, or made, to the contrary in any wise notwithstandyng.</p>
            <p>Prouided also, and be it further enacted by thaucthoritie aforesaid that this acte, or any thing therin cōteined, shall not extende to charge any person, or persones, with any penaltie, or forfeicture, for, or concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng any offence done, or to be done, contrary to the tenour of this act onles he, or thei so offendyng, be sued, or empeched for thesame, within iii. yeres, next after thesame offence be found by enquisition, as is afo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>resaid. This acte to endure for .x. yeres, and from thence, vnto thende of the next parlament.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ The .vi. Chapiter. ¶ An acte for the true makyng of wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len clothe.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here heretofore diuers, and many goodly statu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes haue bene made for the true makyng of clothe within this Realme, Whiche neuerthelesse, foras<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muche as clothiers, some for lacke of knowlege, &amp; experience, and some of extreme couetousnes do daily more, and more, study rather to make many then to make good clothes, hauyng more respecte to theire priuate commoditie and gaine, then the aduauncement of truth, and continuaunce of the cōmoditie in estima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion accordyng to the worthines therof, haue, and do daily, in steade of
<pb facs="tcp:150874:10"/> truthe practise falshod, and in steade of substanciall makyng of clothe, do practise sleight, and slender makyng, some by mynglyng of yarnes of diuers spinnynges in one cloth, some by mynglyng felle woolle, and lambes wolle, or either of theym with fliece wolle, some by puttyng to litle stuffe, some by takyng them out of the mille, before thei be ful thic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, some by ouerstretchyng them vpon the tentour, and then stopping with stocks, such brackes, as shalbe made by meanes therof, finally by vsyng so manye subtile sleightes, and vntruthes, as when the clothes so made, be put in the water, to trie them, they rise out of thesame nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in length, nor breadth, as thei ought to do, and in some place nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rower then some, beside suche cocklyng, bandyng, and diuers other great and notable faultes, as almost canot be thought to be true. And yet neuerthelesse, neither fearyng the Lawes in that case prouided, nor regardyng the estimation of their countrie, do not onelye procure the alneagour, to sette the Kynges seale to suche false, vntrue, and faultie cloth, but do theimselues weaue into thesame, the likenes, and simili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of the Kynges highnes most noble, and imperial Croune, and also the first letter of hys name, whiche should be testimonies of truth, and not a defence of vntruthe, to great slaunder of the king our souereigne Lorde, and the shame of this Lande, and to the vtter destruction of so great and notable commoditie, as the like is not in any foreine nacion Our said souereigne Lorde the Kyng, therfore myndyng to aduaunce al truthe, and to abandonne falsehodde, and also to prouide for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuaunce of thesaid commoditie of cloth makyng, to hys honour, and the commune profite of the realme, hathe by thaduise of the lordes and commons in this present Parlament assembled, caused, aswel diuerse honeste Clothiers, as also diuerse Drapers, Marchaunte Tailours, Clothe workers, Sheremen, and other Artificers, to whome it apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teineth to be examined by certein wise, discrete, and sage knightes and burgesses of this present Parlament, of suche matters as touch aswel the false, as the true makyng of clothes, by whose declaration, consent, agrement and aduise, after diuers &amp; sondry metynges &amp; greate delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate aduise taken in the premisses, by aucthoritie of this present parla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment it is enacted, as hereafter foloweth, to remaine firme, &amp; perfecte, notwithstanding any suggestiōs herafter to be made by any clother, or clothmaker to the contrary, as thei haue in lyke cases heretofore done:</p>
            <p>That is to say, that euery clothe, carsey, piece of frise, and cotton shal be made in suche sorte and fourme, and shal conteine in length, bredth, and weight, as is herein herafter particularly mencioned, vpō such pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ines, penalties, &amp; forfeitures, as be here after expressed and appointed.</p>
            <p>Firste that all, and euery brode Clothe, and Clothes, whiche shalbe made after thesaid feast of S. Michael Tharchaungel next comming within the Shieres of Kente and Sussex, or at the toune of Redyng, or anye of theym, or elles where of lyke makyng, as the Cloth
<pb n="x" facs="tcp:150874:10"/> made there shalbe of, shal cōteine in length at the water, euery piece be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng through wette, betwixt. xx viij. &amp; xxx. yardes of measure that is now customably vsed, &amp; in breadth vij. quarters at the least within the listes by the whole length of the same clothe, the listes of the same clothes to be of lyke makyng, &amp; assise, as thei haue here before tyme bene vsed to be made, &amp; that euery piece of thesaid clothes beyng well scoured, thic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, milled, &amp; fully dried, shalbe in weight &amp; weighe .xc. ł. at the leaste.</p>
            <p>And that al, &amp; euery white clothe &amp; clothes, whiche shalbe made with in the citie of Worcester, cōmonly called long worcesters, &amp; al lyke clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes of lyke makyng, made within the citie of Couentrie, or els where after thesaid feast, shal cōteine in length being wette as is aforesaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt .xxix. &amp; .xxxi. yardes the piece, &amp; to euery yarde one ynche of the stā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>darde, &amp; shalbe of the breadth aboue specified, through out, &amp; by al the lēgth of the whole cloth, &amp; listed, as hath bene accustomed, &amp; beyng wel scoured, thicked, milled, &amp; fully dried, shall weighe .iiij. score .iiij. ł. the piece at the least. And that al coloured clothes made in thesaid cities of Couentrie and Worcester, or els where, of lyke makyng, aftre thesaid feast, shal conteine and be of lyke length, and breadthe as is last afore mencioned, and be listed as is aforesaid, and beyng well scoured, thic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and fully dried, shal weighe .iiij. score ł. the piece at the leaste.</p>
            <p>And that al, &amp; euery white clothe &amp; clothes, commonly called shorte Worcesters, whiche shalbe made within thesaid citie, or countie, or els where, of the same sorte, aftre thesaid feast, shal cōteine in length, beyng wette, betwixt .xxiij. &amp; .xxv. yardes, yarde and ynche of the rule, &amp; shalbe of the breadth as is aforesaid, through out, and by al the whole clothe, and listed accordyng to the auncient custome, and beyng well scoured, thicked, and fully dried, shal weighe .iij. score ł. the piece at the least.</p>
            <p>And that al coloured long clothes, whiche aftre thesaid feaste shalbe made within the shieres of Suffolke, Norfolke, &amp; Essex, or any of them or els where of lyke sorte, shal conteine in length, wette as is aforesaid, betwixt .xxviij. &amp; .xxx. yardes, yarde and ynche of the rule, and shalbe in breadth .vij. quarters of the yarde within the listes at the least, through out, and by all the whole clothe, &amp; listed as hath bene accustomed, and beyng wel scoured, thicked, milled, &amp; fully dried, shal weighe .iiij. score ł. the piece at the least. And that al and euery shorte clothe, and clothes coloured, whiche aftre thesaid feast shalbe made within thesaid shieres last remembred, or any of them, or els where of lyke sorte, shal conteine wette as is aforesaid, betwixt .xxiij. &amp; .xxv. yardes, yarde and ynche of the rule, and shalbe in breadth, as last is remembred, through out, &amp; by the whole clothe, &amp; listed as is aforesaid, and beyng fully scoured, thicked, milled, and fully dried, shal weighe .iij. score .iiii. ł. the piece at the least.</p>
            <p>And that al. &amp; euery coloured cloth, &amp; clothes which aftre thesaid feast shalbe made within thesaid shieres, last remembred, or els where of like sortes, cōmonly called handy warpes, of what lēgth thei shal happē to be, shalbe in breadth out of the water, through out, and by al the whole
<pb facs="tcp:150874:11"/> clothe, as is last remembred, &amp; listed as thei haue bene accustomed, &amp; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng wel scoured, thicked, milled, &amp; fully dried, euery yarde of euery such clothe, shal weighe .iii. ł at the least. And that al whites, whiche aftre thesaid feast shalbe made in thesaid shieres, or els wher, as cockesal whites glainsfordes, &amp; other, beyng handwarpes, of what lengthes soeuer thei shalbe, shal cōteine in breadth as is afore remembred, &amp; be listed as is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresaid, &amp; beyng wel scoured, thicked, milled, &amp; fully dried shal weighe by the yarde .iii. ł at the least, of such measure as hath bene before vsed.</p>
            <p>And that al whites &amp; reddes whiche aftre thesaid feaste shalbe made in the shieres, or counties of Wilteshere, Glocestre, &amp; Somerset, or any of thē, or els wher of lyke making, &amp; al other whites, which shalbe made in any other partes of the Realme, &amp; not afore remembred, shal conteine in length, beyng through wette, betwixt .xxvi. &amp; .xxviii. yardes, &amp; shalbe vii. quarters of the yarde in breadth within the listes at the least, &amp; listed accordyng to the aunciēt custome, &amp; being wel scoured, thicked, milled, &amp; fully dried, shal weighe euery piece .lxiiii. ł. being white, &amp; .iii. score being coloured at the least. And that al brode plunkets, azures, blewes, &amp; other coloured clothe, whiche aftre thesaid feaste shalbe made within thesaid shieres of wilteshere, glocestre, or somerset, or els where of like making, shal conteine beyng wette as is aforesaid, betwixt .xxv. &amp; .xxvii. yardes, yarde &amp; ynche of the rule, &amp; shalbe .vii. quarters of a yarde within the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stes at the least, &amp; listed accordyng to the aunciēt custome, &amp; beyng well scoured, thicked, milled, &amp; fully dried, shal weighe .iii. score .viii. ł. y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> piece at the least. And that al carseis called Ordemaris, shal cōteine in lēgth betwixt .xvii. &amp; .xviii. yardes, yarde &amp; ynche as is aforesaid, &amp; beyng wel scoured, thicked, milled, dressed, &amp; fully dried, shal weighe .xx. ł. at the least.</p>
            <p>And al carseis, called sortyng carseis, which aftre thesaid feast shalbe made in any parte of this the kynges maiesties realme of Englād, shal conteine in lengthe at the water, betwixt .xvii. &amp; .xviii. yardes, yarde and ynche as is aforesaid, &amp; beyng wel scoured, thicked, milled, dressed, and fully dried, ready to be shewed, shal weighe .xxiii. ł. the piece at the least.</p>
            <p>And that al Deuōshere carseis, called douseines, whiche shalbe made aftre thesaid feast, shal cōteine in lēgth at the water, betwene .xii. &amp; .xiii. yardes, yarde &amp; ynche of the rule, &amp; being wel scoured, thicked, milled, &amp; fully dried, shal weighe .xiiii. ł. the piece at the least. And that al &amp; euery brode clothe, &amp; clothes, called Taunton clothes, bridge waters, &amp; other clothes, whiche shalbe made aftre thesaid feast in Taunton, bridge wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, or in other places of lyke sorte, shal conteine at the water in lengthe betwixt .xii. &amp; .xiii. yardes, yarde &amp; ynche of the rule, and in breadth .vii. quarters of a yarde, &amp; euery narowe clothe made aftre thesaid feaste in thesaid townes, or els where of lyke sortes, shal conteine in the water in lengthe, betwixt .xxiii. &amp; .xxv. yardes, yarde &amp; ynche as is aforesaid, &amp; in breadth one yarde of like measure, &amp; euery suche cloth both brode, &amp; na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe, being wel scoured, thicked, milled, &amp; fully dried, shal weighe. xxxiiii ł. the piece at the least. And that al clothes named checke carsey, &amp; strai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes,
<pb n="x" facs="tcp:150874:11"/> whiche shalbe made aftre thesaid feast, shal cōteine beyng wette, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt .xvii. &amp; .xviii. yardes, with the ynches as is aforesaid, &amp; in breadth one yarde at the least, at the water, and beyng wel scoured, thicked, mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and fully dried, shal weighe .xxiiii. ł. the piece at the least.</p>
            <p>And that al &amp; euery Walshe cotton, &amp; cottons, whiche aftre thesaid feast shalbe made, &amp; wrought ready to be solde for a whole piece, shall not be stretched on the tētour, nor otherwise aboue a naile of a yarde in breadth, &amp; shalbe in length .xxxii. goades in the water at the most, and in breadth .iii. quarters of a yarde, at the water at the least, &amp; beyng so ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wrought, euery whole piece therof shal weighe .xlvi. ł. at the least, &amp; euery haulfe piece of Walshe cotton, beyng fulle wrought as is afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said, shal cōteine in length, weighte, and breadth, aftre the same rate.</p>
            <p>And that all Walshe frises, whiche aftre the feaste aforesaid shalbe made &amp; wrought within the shieres of Cardegan, Carmarden, &amp; Pem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broke, or any of them, or els where of like making, ready to be solde for a whole piece, shal conteine in length at the water .xxxvi. yardes, at the most, yarde &amp; ynche of the rule, &amp; in breadthe .iii. quarters of a yarde, &amp; beyng so fully wrought, shal weighe euery whole piece. xl viii. ł. at the least, &amp; euery haulfe piece of Walshe frises, beyng fully wrought as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresaid, shal conteine in length, breadth, &amp; weight aftre the same rate.</p>
            <p>And that al &amp; euery Northerne clothes, which aftre thesaid feast shal be made, shal conteine betwene .xxiii. &amp; .xxv. yardes in length, yarde and ynche of the rule, &amp; in breadth, beyng through wette .vii. quatters of a yarde within the listes at the least, &amp; beyng wel scoured, thicked, milled &amp; fully dried, shal weighe .lxvi. ł. the piece at the least, and euery haulfe piece, called douseines, made aftre thesaid feast, shal conteine in length, betwixt .xii. and .xiii. yardes of measure aforesaid, and, vii. quarters of a yarde in breadthe, as afore, within the listes, and beyng well scoured, thicked, milled, and fully dried, shal weighe .xxxiii. ł. at the least.</p>
            <p>And that all clothe, commonly called Pennistones, or forest whites, which shalbe made aftre the feast aforesaid, shal conteine in length, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng wette, betwixt .xij. &amp; .xiij. yardes, yarde &amp; ynche as aforesaid, and in breadth .vi. quarters, &amp; an halfe quarter out of the water, at the least, &amp; beyng wel scoured, thicked, milled, &amp; fully dried, shal weighe xxviii. ł. the piece at the least. And that al &amp; euery cottons, called Manchestre, Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>castre shiere, and Chestshiere, cottons, whiche shalbe made aftre thesaid feast, fulle wrought to the sale, shalbe in length .xxii. goades, &amp; conteine in breadth .iii. quarters of a yarde in the water, &amp; shal weighe .xxx. ł. the piece at the least. And that al clothes called Māchestre ruggues, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise named Māchestre frises, whiche shalbe made aftre thesaid feast, &amp; fulle wrought to sale, shal cōteine in lēgth xxxvi. yardes, &amp; in breadth. iij quarters of a yarde, cōming out of the water, &amp; shal not be stretched on the taintour, nor otherwise, aboue a naile of a yarde in breadth, &amp; being so fully wrought, &amp; wel dried, shal weighe euery piece xl viii. ł. at y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> least.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted, that all, &amp; euery person, &amp; persons, whiche
<pb facs="tcp:150874:12"/> aftre thesaid feast of S. Michael Tharchaungel nexte commyng shal make, or cause to be made any of the seueral kindes of brode clothes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue rehersed, of any shorter, or longer measure, then is aboue specified &amp; appoincted for euery countrie, or seueral kynde of clothes to be made, or make any suche cloth, or clothes of lesse breadth, or weight, being wel skowred, thicked, milled, &amp; fully dried, then as is aboue specified, &amp; ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for euery seueral countrie, or kindes of clothes, &amp; shal putte the same to sale, shal forfeicte, &amp; lose for euery suche defaulte of euery cloth solde, or offred to be solde, in length or breadth .xl. s̄. &amp; for euery pounde weight, whiche any clothe so made, and solde, or offred to be solde, shal lacke, excedyng not aboue .iiii. ł. in weight, shal also forfeicte .ij. s̄. for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery pounde, the same forfeicture to go to the fynder therof. And that if any suche clothe lacke aboue .iiii. ł. weight, of the seuerall weightes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue mencioned, that euery owner therof shal then forfeicte .xl. s̄. for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery suche clothe so lackyng of his weighte, as is aforesaid.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwaies, that if any brode clothe shal excede the seuerall lengthe before appointed for euery country, or kynde of makyng, by meanes of the finesse, or the good, perfecte, and stuffie makyng of the same clothe, that then the maker therof shall not encurre any losse, or penaltie for the ouerlength of any suche fyne clothe. Any thyng herein to the contrarie in any wyse, notwithstandyng.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted, that al &amp; euery person, or persons, which af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre thesaid feast shal make, or cause to be made any of the seueral kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of carseis, narowe clothes, streightes, douseines, frises, or cottons aboue mencioned, whiche shal not be made in suche maner, &amp; fourme, as is aboue said, nor conteine &amp; haue in length, breadth, &amp; weight seuerally appointed, &amp; limited as is aboue specified, shal lose &amp; forfeicte for euery piece of cloth called streight, or dousein, &amp; for euery piece of narow cloth carsey, frise, or cotton, so to be made, &amp; solde, or offred to be solde .xx. s̄.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted, that frō &amp; aftre thesaid feast, no person, or persons, shal put any heare, flockes, or any yarne made of lābes wolle, in to any cloth, carsey, frise, or cottō, so made &amp; sold, or offred to be sold, vpō paine to forfeicte euery such cloth, carsey, frises, &amp; cottō, wherin any such yarne, heare, or flockes shalbe put, or y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> value of such cloth, carseis, or frise</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted, that if at any tyme, aftre thesaid feast, any clothe through the defaulte, or negligence of the carders, spynners, or weauers, or any of them, shal, or do proue, either pursy, boudy, squally by warpe, or woufe, or els shal happen to be euill burled, or wasted in the mille, or els through the defaulte, or negligence of the mil man, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise to be ful of holes, mille brackes, or to be holy, that thē the seale of the alnegour shal not be fixed, or set to any suche clothe, any law, sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute, or vsage, to the contrarie in any wyse, notwithstādyng, but the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>customable fees, and allowaunces of the alnegour shal neuertheles be paid, vpō paine of forfeicture of suche whole cloth, or the value therof.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted, that if any clothier, or clothemaker do aftre
<pb n="xi" facs="tcp:150874:12"/> thesaid feast, put any clothe, or carsey to sale, before he shal haue paied to the alnegour, or his deputie, the accustomable fee, or agre for thesa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine, as he, she, or they, haue bene accustomed, shall lose, and forfeicte for euery default .xx. s̄.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted, that no persō, or persons, English, denizē, alien, or straunger, shal aftre thesaid feaste cary, or transporte, or cause to be caried, or transported, into any of the partes beyond the sea, any cloth, carsey, frise, or cotton of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> seueral sortes aboue recited, onles the kinges seale, or alnegours seale of this Realme, and the Seale of the owner, or maker of the cloth (declaryng therin the lēgth, of the cloth as it shalbe in the water) be set vpon euery such cloth, vpō pain to forfeict euery suche clothe lackyng thesame seales, or any of them, or the value therof.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted by thaucthoritie aforesaid, that no draper matchaunt tailour, clothworker, or other persō, which shal retaile any of the clothes, or carseis, frises, rugges, or cottons, of the seuerall ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynges aforesaid, shal aftre thesaid feast put to sale, any of the clothes afore mencioned, wherunto the alneagour shal haue set to the kynges seale &amp; y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> owner his seale, til such time, as he or thei haue made trial, as<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wel by the water, as by the weight, &amp; measure, whether thei, &amp; eueri of them shalbe made according to the purporte, and true meaning of this acte, or no. And if any persone, or persones, shal finde any defectiue, or faultie cloth, in lēgth, waight, or measure, made cōtrary to thordre a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresaid, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> thē he, or thei shal present euery suche clothe to euery Maior Bailife, or other hed officer, or hed officers of euery citie, Boroughe, or towne corporate, or to two Iustices of peace next adioynyng oute of a citie, Boroughe, or toune corporate, where such cloth shalbe foūd faul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie as is aforesaide, to thentent thesame cloth may be cut into .iii. equal partes, &amp; pieces. The one piece therof to be forfeited to our souereigne lorde the kyng, an other piece to be to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> presēter therof, &amp; the third part residue to suche person, or persons, as it shal then be presented to, vpon paine that euery suche person, as shal not so serche euery of the clothes carseis, cottōs, or frises aforsaid, so by him to be bought, &amp; solde, &amp; shal not seise, &amp; presēt such cloth, or clothes, as he, or thei shal find defectiue as is aforesaid, shall forfeict, &amp; lose the doble value of euery such cloth.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted that euery clothier, or other persone what soeuer, which so shal sel any suche faultie carsey, cotton, or frise, where vnto the alnegour, &amp; the owner, shal haue set to ther Seales, &amp; shall so be seased, as is aforesaide, shall within .xiiii. daies nexte aftre requeste made by writtyng, message, or otherwise, by such person, which shal so buy suche cloth, make paiment of suche sōmes of money as he receiued for the same, or shal otherwise satisfie, discharge, and acquite him for so muche money as he shall, or shoulde haue receiued for the same, vpon paine of forfaicture to the partie greued for euery non paiment, or not acquict al as is aforesaid the double value of the money so receiued, or
<pb facs="tcp:150874:13"/> to be receiued, thesame to be recouered by bill, plainte, action of debte, or otherwise, in any of the kynges Maiesties courtes of recorde, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in no essoine, protection, or wager of law shalbe admitted, or allowed.</p>
            <p>And for the further auoidyng of muche vntruth practised by stret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chyng of clothes, be it enacted that no person, or persons, shal after thesaide feaste, straine, or stretche, or cause to be strained, or stretched, any clothe, aboue one yarde in lengthe, and one haulfe quarter in breadthe, vpon paine to forfeict for euery suche default .v. ł.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted, that no persone, whiche shal after thesaid feast kepe, haue, vse, or occupie any taintour, shall haue, vse, or occupie, any wrynche, rope, or ryng with thesame tentour, or shal vse any other engine vnlawefully to straine, or stretche, any clothe, or clothes, vpon paine that euery offendour that shal vse, or occupie anye tentour, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther engine to the contrary, shall forfeict .xx. ł.</p>
            <p>And be it also enacted by like aucthoritie, that if any marchaūt shal by any meanes transporte, or cary ouer into the partes beyond the sea any cloth, carsey, frise, or cotton, which shalbe found defectiue, or faul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, either in length, bredth, or weight, or els shal haue any of the faul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes aforesaid, that then the marchaunt, or other person, whiche shall so transport thesame, shal retourne againe thesame clothe, so founde de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectiue, into England, at the costes &amp; charges of the clothier, or clothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maker, that sold thesame clothe, thesame costes, &amp; thinges to be recoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red against suche clothemaker, or clothier by actiō of debt, bill, plaint, or enformation in any of the kynges courtes, any promise, or bargaine to the contrary notwithstandyng: Vpon pain that euery marchaūt, or other person, whiche shal not so returne suche faulty, or defectiue cloth (if through misfortune, by tēpest, pirates, or enemies he be not letted) shal forfeit and lose the value of the cloth so shipped, &amp; trāsported &amp; not retourned as is aforesaid. Thone moitie therof to the kyng, &amp; thother moitie to hym that wil sue for the same by action of debt, vil, plaint, or enformation, in whiche actions no essome, protection, nor wager of Lawe shalbe admitted for the defendaunt.</p>
            <p>And to the entente that it maye bee perfectlye knowen, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che clothes are perfectlye dressed, died, and pressed with the colde Presse, withoute fraude, couine, and deceipte, aswelle within the citie of London, as els where, and haue sufficient workmanshippe: Be it further enacted, that aswel the Maiour of the citie of London, and Aldermen, or the mooste parte of them, for the tyme beyng, as all, and euery other Maiour, Balifie, and other head officer, or officers of euery citie, Borough, or toune corporate, within this realme, shal haue ful power and aucthoritie, by vertue of this acte, to nominate, depute, and appoincte from tyme to tyme, as occasion shall serue, and shall so from tyme to tyme, nominate, depute, and appoinct, two, or mo honest discrete, and expert persones, which shal from time to time vpon their othes, view, and serche, al &amp; euery clothe, and clothes, that shalbe dres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed,
<pb n="xij" facs="tcp:150874:13"/> died, or pressed with the colde presse, within euery suche citie, bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough, towne corporate, or porte towne, &amp; viewe, &amp; searche whether the same cloth, or clothes be wel, &amp; sufficiētly dressed, &amp; pressed with the colde presse, without puttyng therto flockes, sollace, chalke, flower, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deceiptful thyng, &amp; also whether thesame shalbe wel &amp; substantial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly died with good, &amp; perfecte colours without any deceiueable thyng, or whether it shalbe stretched, or strained any more thē is aboue speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied: &amp; shal haue ful power &amp; aucthoritie by vertue of this acte to entre into al &amp; euery persons house, or houses, where thei shal thynke mete, to searche, &amp; to seise al, &amp; euery suche cloth, &amp; clothes, as thei shal fynde de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectiue in the premisses, as forfeicted in whose hādes soeuer thei shalbe founde. The moietie of whiche forfeicture shalbe to the vse of our So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uereigne lord the king, &amp; thother moietie to the vse of the Maiour, &amp; cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munaltie of the city of Londō, or to the vse of euery city, borough, town corporate, porte towne, or market towne, where the same shalbe seised.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted that euery person, or persons, in whose hā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, or possession suche defectiue, or faultie clothe, either by euill, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiueable dyeng, dressyng, or pressyng as is aforesaid, shalbe founde, &amp; seased as is aforesaid, shall haue his, her, or their remedie by action of Debte, Bille, Plainte, enformacion, or otherwise in any of the Kynges Maiesties courtes of recorde, wherin no essoine, protectiō, or wager of lawe shalbe admitted, or allowed for the defendaunt against al, &amp; euery suche person, or persons, by whose defaultes, or negligence suche clothe shal so be founde faultie, and shal therby recouer all suche costes, los<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, and damages as he shal susteine by occasion therof.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted by thesame aucthoritie, that aswel thesaid Maiour of the citie of London, as euery other Maiour, bailife, porte rieue, or other head officer of euery citie, boroughe, towne corporate, or porte towne, shal on thisside thesaid feast, cause to be prepared a seale of leade, wherin aswel the armes, as the name of euery suche citie, borough towne corporate, or porte towne shalbe grauē, which thesame searchers shal cause to be fixed to euery cloth that thei shal finde aftre thesaid feast wel &amp; sufficiently dressed, died, &amp; pressed with the colde presse without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the disceiptes aforesaid, &amp; shal haue for their paines, &amp; trauailes therin to be takē, by the owner therof for the sealing of euery cloth .ij. d.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted that if any searcher, or searchers so to be ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pointed, do aftre thesaid feast find any of the clothes being coloured, or died, so made aftre thesaid feast, either cockly, pursy, boudy, squally, or ro wie, or euil burled, or wasted in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> mille, or ful of holes, or breakes, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> then the same searcher, or searchers shal besides y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> seale of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> citie, borough, or towne corporate, where thesame cloth shalbe foūde, put another seale of leade at euery end of thesaid cloth, wherin shalbe grauē y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> lettre <hi>F.</hi> &amp; shal also set a marke in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> list right against such place, wher any of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> faultes aforesaid shalbe, with the printe of a lettre, or marke of an inche cōpasse
<pb facs="tcp:150874:14"/> at the least, wherby euery buier may wel know what, &amp; where y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> fault is.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted that if any of the seachers aforesaid shall sette the seale of any citie, borough, towne corporate, or porte towne, to any coloured clothe, whiche shal not be sufficiently dressed, died, pressed &amp; wrought, as is aforesaid, that then the Maiour &amp; cōmunaltie, or bai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifes, or cōmunaltie, or other corporacion of the towneshippe by what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer name or names thei shalbe encorporated where suche cloth shal so be sealed, shal forfeicte &amp; lose the whole value of the clothe so seased.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted by the aucthoritie aforesaid, that yf any of the searchers aforesaid, aftre thesaid feast do set to the seale of the citie, borough, or towne corporate within the limites of their searche to any clothe whiche shalbe cockely, pursey, baudie, squallie, rewie, euil butled wasted in the mille or ful of holes, as is aforesaid, and not sette at eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ende of thesaid clothes one seale with the lettre <hi>F.</hi> as is aforesaid, &amp; also declare by the listes as is aforesaid, what, and where the faultes of the clothe be: that then the Maiour and communaltie, or other the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poracion of euery suche borough, citie, or towne corporate, where suche searcher shalbe appointed, shal forfeicte, and lose for euery suche omis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, or not settyng to of any suche seale as is aforesaid .v. ł.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted that no person, or persons whatsoeuer thei be, whiche cōmunely vse to retaile clothe, or carsey, shall put to sale, in grosse, or by retaile to any maner of person, any maner of clothe whiche shalbe made aftre thesaid feast, beyng dressed, died, &amp; pressed as is afore said, excepte there be fixed therunto at euery ende of the same clothe, the seale of suche citie, borough, or towne corporate, where the same clothe shalbe so died, dressed, &amp; pressed, or the seueral seale of euery suche citie, borough, or towne corporate, where it shalbe died, dressed, or pressed, to remaine at the laste ende of euery of thesaid clothe, whiche shalbe solde duryng, &amp; by al the tyme, that any piece, or rēnaumt of suche cloth is to be solde, vpō paine of forfeicture the whole value of suche whole cloth.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted, that euery Maiour, Bailife, or other head officer of any Citie, Borough, or towne corporate, in whiche any suche clothe, or clothes aftre thesaid feast shalbe made, died, dressed, or pressed with the colde presse as is aforesaid, whiche doeth not, or shal not aftre thesaid feast of S. Michael nominate &amp; appoint from tyme to tyme so many searchers as shalbe requisite to viewe and searche clothes vpon their othes as is aforesaid, shal lose, &amp; forfeicte for euery default .x. ł.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted that if any of thesaid searchers so to be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by the Maiour beyng a fre man of thesaid citie, or by the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iour, Bailife, or other head officer of any Citie, Boroughe, or Towne corporate as is aforesaid, hauyng no reasonable excuse, do refuse to take vpon hym to be a searcher, and do not vse the office of a searcher, as is aforesaid shal forfeicte &amp; lose for euery suche refusal, and not exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutyng of his office so to hym appointed .v. ł. The one haulfe therof to
<pb n="xiij" facs="tcp:150874:14"/> be to the kyng our souereigne lorde, and thother half, to the vse of the communaltie of euery citie, borough, or towne corporate, where he shal so be assigned, and to remayne in warde till suche tyme, as he hath ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de paiment of thesaid forfeicture, or otherwise put in sufficient bondes for the satisfaction of thesame. And forasmuche as there be now in this time many false, and deceiuable colours made, in diuers places of this realme, wherby many of the kynges louyng subiectes are deciued,</p>
            <p>Be it enacted, that from and after thesayd feaste of sainct Michael Tharchaungel next commyng, no persone, or persones, shal put to sale by retayle within this realme, any clothe, or clothes, whiche shalbe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de after thesaid feaste, of any other coloure, or coloures, then is hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter expressed, that is to saie, Skarlet, redde, Crymosen, murrey, Violet, puke, broun, blew, blackes, grenes, yellowes, blewes, Orenge tawney, cusset, marble gray, sad, newe colour, Azure, watchet, Shepes coloure, Lion colour, Mottley, or yron gray, vpon paine that euery persone of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendyng to the contrary, shall lose and forfeicte the valew of the cloth solde by retayle, whiche shalbe of any other coloure.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted, that no persone, or persones, after thesaid feaste of saincte Michaell Tharchaungell, shall presse any kynde of clothe, with the whote presse, or in any other kynd of deceiuable maner, but only with the cold presse, as is aboue specified, vpon payne of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feicture of the whole clothe so pressed contrary to the meanyng of this statute, or the valewe thereof.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted, that if any persone, or persones, but suche as are appoincted, assigned, and permitted, by this acte, do at any time after thesaid feast, counterfecte, sette to, or take away frō any of the clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes, Carseis, frisys, rugges, or cottons aforesaide, any of the seales so to be fixed, as is aboue recited, that then euery persone so offendyng, shall for the firste offence (beyng therof duely conuicted, by verdicte of xij. men, by two sufficient witnesses, or by confession of the partie) for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feicte, and lose .x. ł. and for the seconde offence (beyng likewise therof cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uicted) shall sitte on the pillourie, and lose, &amp; forfeicte, to our souereigne lorde the Kyng, all suche his goodes and cattalles (his debtes beyng duely &amp; truly payde, without fraude or couine) as he had, or shall haue at the tyme of his conuiction.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted, that if betwene the first day of May next commyng, and the feaste of saincte Michael Tharchaungel, then next commyng, any persone, or persones, whiche nowe dothe vse the arte or mistery of drapyng, or cloth makyng, shall geue ouer drapyng or cloth makyng, excepte he be licenced so to do, by thre iustices of peace, at the leaste, of the citie, countie, borough, or toune corporate, where he dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth, vpon some reasonable cause shewed vnto thesaid iustices, shall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer after take vpon hym to make, or cause to be made, any kynde of cloth or carsey, to sel thesame agayne, vpon payne of forfeicture of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb facs="tcp:150874:15"/> suche clothe or carsey that he shall so sell.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted, that all and euery article, clause, or senten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, in any acte of parlament heretofore made, concernyng makyng, dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eng, dressyng, pressyng, serchyng, or sealyng, of any of the kyndes of clothes, brode or narrowe, white or coloured carseis, frises, rugges or cottons, heretofore in this acte mencioned, and beyng repugnaunt, or contrariant to any article or sentence in this statute, shall fro the feaste of sainct Michaell Tharchaungell next, be vtterly voyde, and of none effecte. And to thentent, that all suche clothes as shalbe made within this realme, or any other the kynges dominiōs, after thesaid feast, shal be the better knowen frō the other clothes made before thesame tyme:</p>
            <p>Be it therefore enacted by the aucthoritie aforesayde, that from af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the sayde feaste, the letter. E. crouned, shall not be wrought into the clothe, for, and by the space of two yeres then next ensuyng, vpon paine of forfeicture of twenty. s̄. for euery clothe or carsey, wherein thesayde letter. E. shall so be wrought, the moytie of all whiche forfeicture and of all other forfeictures before expressed, and not otherwise appoincted by this present Acte, shall be to the kyng our souereigne lorde, and the other moytie, to hym or them that will sue for thesame, by accion of debte, detinewe, bil, playnte, or informacion, in any of the kynges cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of recorde, wherein no wager of lawe, essoyne, or protection shalbe admitted nor allowed for the defendaunt.</p>
            <p>Prouided also, and be it enacted by thaucthoritie abouesayde, that it shall not be lawfull to any persone, or persones, at any tyme after the feaste of saincte Michaell Tharchaungell next commyng, to boyle or cause to be boyled, any kynde of wolles, to be conuerted into any kind of brode clothe, or Carsey, with any kynde of galles, tyndes, barkes of trees, or sawe dust, vpon payne to forfeicte all suche wolle, or the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue thereof, to be recouered, and had in suche fourme and sorte, as in the foresaide acte is limited and expressed.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwaies, that this acte or any thyng therein conteyned, shal not in any wise extende to any clothe or clothes, made in the toune of Tauestocke, in the countie of Deuonshiere, or els where within the sayde countie, commonly called Tauestocke clothes, but that it shalbe lawfull to all and euery enhabitauntes of thesaid toune, or ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of thesayd clothes, commonly called Tauestockes, to make and sell thesame with the accustomed seale, as they haue heretofore bene accustomed, any thyng in this acte to the contrary, in any wyse notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standyng.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="chapter">
            <pb n="xiiij" facs="tcp:150874:15"/>
            <head>The .vij. Chapiter. ¶ An acte limityng the tymes for buyeng and sellyng of Wolles.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or asmuche as the great plentie of wolles within this Realme, ought by all reason to cause thesame to be of conuenient and resonable prices, yet by the gredy and couetous myndes, aswell of suche as haue the great plenty and aboundaunce of Shepe and wolles, as also by the corrupte practises of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers Broggers', engrossers, wolle gatherers, and regratours, and sondrie other persones, by the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng to muche libertie of buyeng, keping, vsyng, and occupieng of the same wolles, it manifestly appereth, that the prices therof be wōderful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and excedyngly enhaunced and raysed, to the great hurt, detryment, and decaie of the Realme.</p>
            <p>Be it therefore ordeined, establyshed, and enacted, by aucthoritie of this present Parlamente, that no maner of persone, or persones, beyng borne within the Kynges obeisaunce, shall after the laste daie of May nexte, buye, bargayne, take or make, any promes, or bargayne of wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, but onely suche persone or persones, his wife, or his, or their Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prentice, or Apprentices, enhabityng in his, or their mansion house, or houses, as shall of thesayde wolles make yarne, any kynde of cloth, chā<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>blettes, wolsteade, Sayes, Stamyne, knytte Hose, knitte Peticotes, knitte gloues, knitte slieues, hattes, coyues, cappes, arrasse, tapesserie, couerlectes, gyrdles, or any other thyng vsed to be made of wolle, or myxed with wolle within the realme: or elles a merchaunt or merchaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes of Thestaple at Calleis, or his, or their apprentice, or apprentices, dwelling in his or their, mansion house, or houses, to be shipped only to thestaple at Calleis, vpon payne of forfeicture of the double value of thesayde wolles so to be bought, or bargayned, or taken by promyse of bargayne, contrary to this present acte.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted by the aucthoritie aforesayde, that no mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaunt straunger, after the .xx. daie of Aprill next commyng, by hym selfe, or by any other persone or persones for hym, in his name, or to his vse, in any yere after thesayd .xx. daie of Aprill then to come, shall bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne or buye any wolles, before the feast of the Purificatiō of our la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy next after the clippyng or shearyng of thesame wolles, vpon payne of forfeicture of the double value of thesame wolles.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted by the aucthoritie aforesayde, that no ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of persone or persones, hauyng any wolle or wolles, of his or their owne groweth, shall at any tyme after the feaste of the Natiuitie of saincte Ihon Baptiste next comming, kepe thesame wolles, to thentent
<pb facs="tcp:150874:16"/> to sell thesame in wolle vnwrought, ouer and aboue one whole yeare next and immediatly after the sheryng of thesame wolles: So as there be offered without fraude or couine to the owner or owners thereof, within thesame tyme, suche price as then shalbe moste communely ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen in thesame Shiere for wolle of like goodnesse and packyng, vpon payne of forfeicture for euery todde or todde weyght thereof so kepte aboue one yeare vnsolde, as is aforesayde, the somme of .x. s̄. the moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of all and euery suche forfeiture and forfeitures, penaltie or penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties before rehersed, to be to the vse of our souereigne lorde the Kyng, his heires and successours, and the other half to the vse of him that wil sue for thesame in any of the Kynges courtes of Recorde, by Action of debte, byll, playnt, informacion, or otherwyse, wherin no wager of lawe, protection or essoyne shalbe allowed for the defendaunt.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwaies, that the Merchanntes of Newe Castle, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther persones, may buye wolles of the groweth of the counties of Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chumberlande, Cumberlande, Westmerlande, Rychemonde, and Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerton Shiere, or the Bisshopricke of Duresme, to thentent to shyppe or transporte thesame into the partes beyonde the Sea, as they haue bene accustomed, any thyng in this Statute to the contrary, in any wyse notwithstandyng.</p>
            <p>Prouided also and be it enacted, that the Merchauntes of the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, maie from tyme to tyme, bargayne, or selle, their refuse course wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, and locques, suche as is not mete for thesayde Staple, to any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sone, or persones, that will buye thesame to make Yarne or Clothe, or other thynges as is abouesayde, within this Realme, so as the same be shotte and packed by the wolle packer, declaryng of what packyng or countrey the refuse or locques be, and writyng vpon the clothes wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in thesayd refuse wolle is packed, in great lettres, as they do vpon the wolles that is shypped to Calais.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwaies and be it enacted by thaucthoritie abouesayde, that it shall and may be lawfull to the Kynge our souereigne Lorde by his proclamacion, at any tyme hereafter to be made and sette furth, to repeale this Statute, and all and euery article, clause, sentence, and other thyng, and thynges, therein conteyned, and to make thesame voyde to all ententes, and purposes, as thoughe this Acte had neuer bene had or made, any thyng in this Statute to the contrary, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standyng.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwaies, that the Acte made at the firste session of thys Parlament holden, in the firste yeare of the reygne of out souereygne lorde the Kyng, called and entitled the Acte for the continuaunce of makyng of Worsted yarne in Norfolke, and euery article and clause thereof, shall remayne and continue in full force, vertue and strength. And that all persones enhabityng, or that shall enhabite, within the sayde Countie of Norfolke, or Citie of Norwiche, and euery of them
<pb n="xv" facs="tcp:150874:16"/> shall and may buye, and sell wolles growyng within thesayde Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of Norfolke, accordyng to the purporte, true effect, and plaine mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng of thesayde acte, made in thesayde firste yere of the reigne of or sayde souereigne Lorde the Kyng, any thyng in this acte conteyned to the contrary thereof, in any wyse notwithstandyng.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ The .viij. Chapiter. ¶ An Acte limityng what persones shall weaue or make brode wollen clothe.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>E it enacted by the assent of the Kynges Maiestie the Lordes spirituall, and temporal, and the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons in this Parlamente assembled, and by the aucthoritie of thesame, that no persone, or perso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes within this Realme of Englande, Wales, or other the Kynges Dominions, after the feaste of saincte Michaell the Archaungell next ensuyng, shall weaue, or make, or put to weauyng, or ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng, any maner of brode wollen clothe, or brode wollen clothes, to be solde, oneles that suche persone, or persones, that shall so weaue or make, or put to weauyng, or makyng, thesayde brode wollen clothe, or clothes, so to be made to be solde, haue bene an Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prentice to the occupacion of brode wollen clothe makyng, or clothes weauyng, or haue bene exercised and practised in, and with brode clothe makyng, or clothe weauyng, by the space of seuen yeares at the least, before thesame persone, or persones, shall so take vpon hym, or them, to make, or weaue, or to putte to weauyng, or makyng, thesayde brode wollen clothes, vpon payne to forfeicte all, and euery suche clothe, and clothes, so wouen, or made, contrarie to the fourme of this acte: the one halfe of whiche forfeicture, shalbe to our souereigne lorde the Kyng, and the other halfe, to hym or them, that will, or shall, sue for thesame, by byll, playnte, action of debte, or enformacion, in any courte of Recorde, within this Realme of Englande, or Wales, in whiche action, sute, playnt, bil, or infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macion, no essoyne, protection, or plea to the iurisdiction of the Courte, shall be allowed for the defendaunt.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:150874:17"/>
            <head>¶ The .ix. Chapiter. ¶ An acte that no man robbyng any house, Bouthe, or Tente, shalbe admitted to the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite of his Clergie.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here at the Parlament holdē at Westminster, by prorogacion, in the .xxiii. yeare of the reigne of the late king of famous memory, kyng Henry the viii It was among other thinges, then and there enac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted, established, and ordeined, by aucthoritie of the same parlamēt, that no persone nor persones, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che after that time should happen to be found gil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, after the lawes of this Realme, for any maner petie treason, or for any wilful murther of malice prepensed, or for rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byng of any churches, chapelles, or other holy places, or for robbyng of any persone, or persones, in their dwellyng houses, or dwellyng pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, the owner or dweller in thesame house, his wife, his children, or ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntes, then beyng within, and put in feare, or dread by thesame, or for robbyng of any person, or persons, in or nere about the high waies or for wilfull burnyng of any dwellyng houses, or barnes, wherin any grayne, or corne, should happen to be, nor any persone, or persones, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng founde giltie of any abattement, procurement, mainteining, or cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealyng of any, or to any suche petie Treason, murthers, or Fellonies, should from thencefurth be admitted to the benefite of his, or their cler<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gie, but vtterly to be excluded thereof, and suffre death, in suche maner and fourme, as they should haue done for any the causes, or offences abouesayde, if they were no clerkes, suche as be within the holy orders, that is to saie, of the orders of Subdeacon or aboue, alonely excepted, as by thesame acte amonges other thynges more playnely appereth, whiche acte was made to endure vntill the last daie of the next parla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and after that at the session of the parlament holden at Westmin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ster by prorogacion, in the .xxij. yere of the reigne of thesayd late kyng thesame acte with other actes, was made to continue for euer. Sythen the makyng of whiche statute, it hath bene doubted, that if suche rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beries and fellonies, hath bene committed and done in dwellyng hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, and dwellyng places, the owner, or dweller, in thesame houses, his wife, his children, or seruaūtes, beyng then put in feare, or dread, by the same shal not lose the benefite of their clergie, if the offendours be ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>in founde giltie by the lawes of this realme, onles thesame robberie, or fellonie be cōmitted and done, in the very chāber, house, or place, where the owner or dweller, in thesame house, his wife, childrē or seruauntes, shall happen to be, or lie at the time of suche robberie, and fellonie com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted &amp; done, and put in feare or dread, although the owner &amp; dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler in suche house, and houses, his wife, his children, or seruauntes, at
<pb n="xvi" facs="tcp:150874:17"/> the time of suche robberie, and fellonie committed, &amp; done, were or laye in other places, within the precinct of thesame dwellyng houses, nyghe vnto the house, or place, where suche robberie, and fellonie shall happē to be done. Or if it happen that the owner, or dweller, within thesame house where suche robberie, &amp; fellonie, shal happen to be done, his wife children, or seruauntes, to be aslepe, at the time of suche robberie, &amp; tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonie, cōmitted &amp; done, although thesame robberie were done in the chā<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ber, or place, where the owner or dweller in thesame house, his wife, chil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dren, or seruauntes, then laie, the offendours beyng founde giltie there of accordyng to the lawes of the lande, should not lose the benefite and aduauntage of his Clergie: And where also it hath bene in question, &amp; doubted, that if suche robberies, and fellonies, happen to be cōmitted, and done, in any bouth, or bouthes, tent, or tētes, in any faier or market the owner of thesame, his wife, childrē or seruauntes, happē to be with in thesame, at the time of the cōmittyng of suche fellonies, &amp; put in feare and dread, the offendours therein beyng founde giltie, after the lawes of this realme, should not lose the benefite of their clergie. For the true declaratiō &amp; explanaciō of thesame doubtes, or questiōs before recited</p>
            <p>Be it enacted, ordeined, and established, by the kyng our souereigne lorde, the lordes spirituall, and temporall, and the cōmons in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent parlament assembled, and by the aucthoritie of thesame, that if it happen any persone, or persones, to be founde giltie, accordyng to the lawes of this realme, for robbyng of any persone, or persons, after the first day of May next ensuyng, in any parte or parcel of their dwelling houses, or dwellyng places, the owner, or dweller, in thesame house, or his wife, his children, or seruauntes, being then within thesame house, or place, where it shal happen thesame robbery, &amp; fellonie, to be cōmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and done, or in any other place within the precinct of thesame house or dwellyng place, that suche offēdours, shall in no wise be admitted to their Clergie, whether the owner or dweller in thesame house, his wife, or children, then, and there beyng, shalbe wakyng, or sleping. And that no persone, nor persones, whiche after thesaide first day of May, shall happen to be founde giltie, after the lawes of this Realme, of, and for robbyng any persone, or persones, in any bouthe, or tente, in any fayre or market, the owner, his wife, his children, or seruauntes, or seruaunt then beyng within thesame bouthe, or tente, shall not from hencefurthe be admitted to the benefite of his, or their Clergie, but vtterly be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded thereof, and suffre death, in suche maner and fourme, as is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mencioned in thesayde acte, made in thesayde .xxiij. yeare of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>igne of thesame late Kyng, for robberies, and fellonies, committed, and done, in dwellyng houses, and dwellyng places, the owner, or dweller, in thesame, his wife, children, or setuaūtes, then beyng within thesame and put in feare &amp; dread, without hauyng any respect or consideracion whether the owner or dweller in suche Bouthes, and Tentes, his wyfe <pb facs="tcp:150874:18"/> childrē or seruaūtes, beyng in thesame Bouthes, or Tentes at the time of suche, robberies and fellonies, cōmitted, shalbe slepyng, or wakyng.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="10" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ The .x. Chapiter. ¶ An acte to take away the benefite of Clergie from suche as robbe in one shiere, and flie into another.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here in the parlamēt holdē at Westminster, vpō pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rogacion the .xv. day of Ianuary, in the .xxv. yere of the reigne of our late souereigne lorde Kyng Henry the eighte: It is recited that at the parlament holden at Westminster, in the .xxiii. yere of the reigne of thesaide late kyng, amonges other thynges, it was or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deined, established, and enacted, that no persone, nor persones, whiche after that time should happen to be found giltie after the lawes of this lande, of any maner of petie treason, or for any wilful murther of malice prepensed, or for robbyng of any churches, chapel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, or other holie places, or for robbyng of any persone, or persones, in their dwellyng houses, or dwellyng place, the owner or dweller in the same house, his wife, his children, or seruaūtes, then beyng within, and put in feare &amp; dread by thesame, or for robbyng of any persone, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sones, in, or nere about the high way, or for wilful burning of any dwel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ling houses, or barnes, wherin any grayne of cornes, should happen to be, nor any persone, or persones, beyng found giltie of any abbettemēt, procurement, helpyng, maintenyng, or concelyng, of, or to any such pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie treason, murthers, or fellonies, should from thencefurthe be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, to the benefite of his, or their Clergie, but should vtterly be exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded therof and suffre death, in suche maner and fourme, as they should haue done for any the causes or offences aboue sayde, if they ware no clerckes, whiche acte extended, but only wher suche offendour was cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uicted in suche countie or place, where suche offence was so committed and done, and not where he, or thei, did suche offence in one countie, and were taken with the maner in another countie. Wherfore it was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidered, that for asmuche, as diuers and many fellōs, and robbers, that committe and do, diuers and many great heynous robberies, and bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glaries, in one shiere, &amp; conueie the spoyle and robberie into any other shiere, and there be taken, endicted, and arreigned of fellonie, of the fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonous stealyng of thesame goodes, in thesame other shiere, then where thesame robberies, or burglaries, were done, and cōmitted, in thesame Shiere, where they be so endicted, and arreigned, and that by reason therof, suche fellons, robbers, and burglaries, had, and enio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yed the priuilege, and aduauntage of their clergie.</p>
            <p>For redresse whereof, it was enacted in thesayde Parlament holden in thesayde fyue and twenty yeare of thesayde late Kyng, that if any
<pb n="xvij" facs="tcp:150874:18"/> persone or persones, after that tyme, after suche robberie or burgla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, by hym or them done in one Countie, should be endicted of fellonie for stealyng of any goodes or cattalles, in any other Countie within this Realme, and there vpon arreigned and founde giltie, or stande mute of malice, or chalenge peremptorie aboue the nombre of twenty persones, or would not vpon his or their sayde arreignement directly aunswere to thesame fellonie, that then thesame persone, and persones, so arreigned, and founde giltie, or standyng mute of malice, or chalen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyng peremptorie aboue the nōbre of twenty persones, or that woulde not directly aunswere to the lawe, should lose and be put from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite of his or their Clergie, in like maner and fourme, as they should haue bene, if they had bene endicted, arreigned, and founde giltie in the same Countie where suche robberie, or burglarie, as is aforesayd, was done or committed, if it shuld appere to the iustices before whome any such felons or robbers shuld be arreigned, by euidēce geuen before thē or by examinaction, that thesame felons &amp; burglares, should haue bene put from their Clergie in case thei had bene endited, arreigned, &amp; found giltie in thesame Countie, where thesame robberies or burglaries wer committed or done, as in thesame Statute made in the sayde .xxv. yere among other thynges more playnly appereth. And where in the parla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment holden at Westminster, the fourth daie of Nouember, in the first yere of the reigne of out souereigne lorde the kyng that nowe is:</p>
            <p>It is ordeined and enacted, amonges other thinges, that no persone or persones, that before that time had bene, or at any time after should be, in due forme of the lawes atteynted, or conuicted of murther, of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice prepensed, or of poysonyng of malice prepensed, or of breakyng of any house, by daie or by nyght, any persone beyng then in thesame house, where thesame breakyng had bene, or after that tyme should be cōmitted, beyng put in feare or dread, or of, or for robbyng of any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sone, or persones in the hygh waye, or nere to the hygh waye, or for fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonious stealing of horses, geldinges or mares, or of fellonious taking of any goodes out of any paroche churche, or other Churche, or Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, or beyng indicted or appealed, of any of thesame offences, and ther vpon founde giltie, by verdicte of .xii. men, or should confesse thesame vpon his or their arreignement, or would not aunswere directly, accor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dyng to the lawes of this realme, or should stande wilfully, or of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice mute, should not be admitted to haue or enioye the priuilege or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite of his or their Clergie, or Sanctuarie, but should be put from thesame. And that in all other cases of fellonie, other then suche as be before mencioned, all and singuler persone, &amp; persones, whiche after the first daie of Marche then next followyng should be areigned or found giltie vpon his or their arreignement, or should confesse thesame, or stande mute in fourme aforesayde, or would not aunswere directly in fourme abouesayde, should haue and enioye the priuilege and benefite
<pb facs="tcp:150874:19"/> of his, or their Clergie, and the libertie and priuilege of Sanctuary, in lyke maner and fourme as he, or they myght, or should haue done, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the .xxiiij. daye of Aprill, in the first yeare of the reigne of thesayde late Kyng Henry the eyght, as in thesayde acte, made in thesayde firste yere among other thynges more playnely appereth, by reason of whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che article, and clause, conteined in thesayde acte, made in thesaide first yere, thesaide statute made in thesaide .xxv. yere of thesayde late kyng, whiche did put suche fellones and burglares, from their Clergie, that doe suche offence in one Countie, and after are taken with the goodes stolen in another Countie, and there endicted, arreygned, and founde giltie, was made voyde. By reason wherof, diuers and many persones that sythen thesayde first yere haue committed suche robberies &amp; burg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laries, in one Countie, and after haue bene taken with the maner in an other Countie, and there endicted, arreined, and found giltie haue had and enioyed their Clergie, whiche they could not haue had in case the sayde acte, made in thesayde .xxv. yere, had stande in force, to the greate boldyng and comforte of suche offendours.</p>
            <p>For redresse whereof from hencefurth to be had, be it enacted by auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of this present parlament, that thesayd acte made in thesayde xxv. yere, touchyng the puttyng of suche offendours from their Clergie and euery article, clause and sentence, conteined in thesame, touchyng Clergie, shall from hencefurth touchyng suche offences, frō hencefurth to be committed and done, stande remayne, and be in full strength and vertue, in suche maner and fourme, as it did before the makyng of the sayde acte, made in thesayde firste yere of the reigne of our sayde soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigne lorde the kyng that nowe is, any clause, article, or sentence, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prised in thesayde acte, made in thesayd first yere, to the contrary there of notwithstandyng.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="11" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ The .xi. Chapiter. ¶ An acte for the punyshement of diuets Treasons.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>OR asmuche as it is moste necessarie, both, for cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon pollicie, and dutie of subiectes aboue al thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges to prohibite, restrayne and extincte, all maner of shamefull Slaunders, whiche myght growe, happen, or aryse to their souereigne lorde the kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges Maiestie, whiche when they be heard, sene or vnderstande, cannot be but odible and also abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of all those sortes that be true and louyng sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes, if in any poyncte they may, doe, or shall touche his Maiestie, vpon whome dependeth the whole vnitie and vniuersall weale of this realme, without prouidyng wherfore, to great a scope of vnreasonable libertie should be geuē to al cancted &amp; traiterours hartes, &amp; the kinges
<pb n="xviij" facs="tcp:150874:19"/> louyng subiectes should not declare vnto their souereigne lorde nowe being, which vnto them hath bene, and is moste entierly both beloued, and estemed, their vndoubted sinceritie and truthe.</p>
            <p>Be it therefore enacted, by thassent, and consente of our souereigne lorde the kyng, and the lordes spiritual and temporal, and the cōmons of this present parlament assembled, and by thaucthoritie of thesame, that if any persone or persons, after the first day of Iune next cōming, by open preaching, expresse wordes or sayenges, do expressely directly, and aduiledly, sette furthe and affirme, that the Kynge that nowe is, is an hereticke, scismatike, tiraūt, infidele, or vsurpet of the croune, or that any his heires or successours, to whom the croune of this Realme is li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited by aucthoritie of parlamente, holden in the .xxxv. yeare of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ygne of the late Kyng Henry the eyghte, beyng in lawfull possession of the croune, is an hereticke, scismaticke, tyraunt, infidele, or vsurper of the croune: That then euery suche offendour beyng thereof duely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uicted or atteynted by the lawes of this Realme, their abbettours, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curours and counseilours, and al and euery their aydours, &amp; comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours, knowyng thesayde offences, or any of them to be done, for his or their suche firste offence, shall lose and forfeicte to the kyng, all his and their goodes, and cattalles, and also shall haue and suffre imprisonne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, of his and their bodies, at the Kynges will and pleasure. And if any persone beyng ones conuicted, or atteinted, of any of thesayde of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences, shal after his saide conuiction, or atteinder eftsones cōmitte, or perpetrate any of the offences before mencioned, in fourme aforesayde committed, and shalbe thereof duely conuicted or atteinted, by the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes of this Realme, that then euery suche offeundour and offendours, their abbettours, procurours, &amp; counscilours, &amp; al and euery their ay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours, and comfortours, knowyng thesaide offences, or any of them to be done, for his or their seconde offence or offences, shall lose and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feicte vnto the kyng, the whole yssues and profectes, of al his and their landes, tenementes, and other hereditamentes, benefices, prebendes, &amp; other spirituall promocions, for terme of the lyfe, of suche offendour or offendours, and shall also lose and forfeicte vnto the kyng, all his and their goodes, and cattalles, and also suffre, duryng his and their lyues perpetuall imprisonnement of his and their bodies.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwaies, that suche of thesayde Spirituall promocions, as shalbe charged with cure, be alwaies by the Kynges Maiestie, and his heyres and successours, sufficiently furnysshed of a Curate, for the discharge of thesame. And if any persone beyng twoo tymes hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter conuicted or atteynted, of any of thesame offences, in fourme a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresayde committed, shall after hys seconde conuiction or atteyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, eftsones committe or perpetrate agayne, any of the sayde offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in fourme aforesayde, and be thereof duely conuicte or atteyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, by the lawes and Statutes of this Realme, that then euery suche
<pb facs="tcp:150874:20"/> thirde offence or offences, shalbe deined and adiudged hyghe Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, and the offendour or offendours therein, their abbettours, procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, and counseilours, and al and euery their aydours, and comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours, knowyng thesaid offences, or any of them to be done, beyng ther of conuicted, or atteinted, accordyng to the lawes and statutes of this realme, shalbe iudged and demed hygh traitours, and shall suffre pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of death, and lose and forfeicte all their goodes, and cattalles, lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, and tenementes, wherof he, or they, shalbe seyed of an estate of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritaunce, in his, or their owne right, to the kyng, as in cases of hyghe treason.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted by thaucthoritie aforesaid, that if any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sone, or persones, at any time after thesayd first day of Iune next com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myng by writyng, printyng, paintyng, karuyng, or grauyng, do di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly, expressely, and aduisedly publishe, set furth and affirme, that the kyng that nowe is, or any his heires, or successours, limited as is afore<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sayde, is an hereticke, schismaticke, tyraunt, infidell, or vsurper of the croune, that then euery suche offence and offences, shalbe demed and adiudged hyghe treason, and the offendour, and offendours, their ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bettours, procurours, and counsayllours, and all and euery their ay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours and comfortours, knowyng thesayd offences, or any of them to be done, beyng thereof conuicted or atteinted, accordyng to the lawes &amp; statutes of this realme, shalbe deamed and adiudged hygh traitours, and shall suffre paynes of deathe, and lose and forfeicte all their goo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des and cattalles, landes and tenementes, to the Kynge, as in cases of hygh treason.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted by thaucthoritie aforesaid, that if any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sone, or persones, after thesaide first day of Iune next cōmyng, rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously do deteine, kepe, or withholde, from our said souereigne lorde, his said heires, or successours, any of his or their castles, fortresses, fortiles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, or holdes within this realme, or in any other the kynges dominiōs or marches, or rebelliously, kepe, deteine, or withholde frō the Kynges said highnes, his said heires, or successours, any of his or their shippes ordinaunces, artillerie, or other munitions, or fortificatiōs of warre &amp; do not obediēly render &amp; geue vp to our said souereigne lord, his sayde heires or successours, or to suche persones as shalbe deputed by theim, or any of thē, suche castelles, fortresses, fortilesses, holdes, shippes, ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naūces, artillerie, or other munitiōs, &amp; fortificatiōs of warre, rebelliousli kept, &amp; deteined, within sixe daies next after they shalbe cōmaunded by our said souereigne lord, his said heires, or successors, by opē proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion vnder the great seale, thesame proclamaciō to be made in such pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce &amp; order, so as the partie &amp; parties to be charged by this acte, may cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueniently haue notice or knowledge therof: that then euery suche per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sone, or persons, so offēding, in any the premisses, after thesaid first day of Iune, their abbettours, procurours, &amp; counseilours, &amp; al &amp; eueri their
<pb n="xix" facs="tcp:150874:20"/> aidours and comfortours, knowyng thesaied offences, or any of them, to bee doen, beyng lawfully conuicted, of the rebelliously kepyng, and deteinyng thereof, accordyng to the lawes and statutes of this realme, shalbee adiudged traitours, and shall suffer paines of death, and lose and forfeict al their goodes and cattelles, landes and tenementes, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the kyng, as in cases of high treason.</p>
            <p>And ouer that, be it enacted by the aucthoritie aforesaied, that if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the Kynges subiectes, Denisens, or other, do commit, or practise, out of the limites of this realme, in any outward partes, any the offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, whiche by this acte are made, or heretofore now standyng in force, haue been made treason, that then suche treasons, whatsoeuer thei bee, or where soeuer thei shall happen, so to bee dooen or committed, shalbe enquired and presented, by the othes of .xii. good and lawfull men, vpō good and probable euidence and witnesse, in suche Shiere and countie of this Realme, and before suche persones, as it shall please the Kyng, his saied heires, or successours, to appoynet by Commission, vnder his greate Seale, in like maner and forme, as treasons committed within this realme, haue been vsed to bee enquired of, and presented. And that vpon euery endictment and presentment, founden &amp; made of any suche treasons, and certefied into the kynges Benche, like processe and other circumstaunce shalbe there made, and had against the offendours, as if thesame treason so presented, had been lawfully found to bee doen, and committed, within the limites of this Realme. And that all processe of outlawrie, hereafter to be made and had, within this realme, against a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny offendours in treason, beyng resiaunt, or enhabitaunt, out of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites of this realme, or in any the partes beyond the sea, at the tyme of the outlawrie pronounced against them, shalbe as good and effectuall in the Lawe, to all ententes and purposes, as if any suche offendours, had been residēt and dwellyng within this realme, at the tyme of suche processe awarded, and outlawrie pronounced.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwaies, and be it enacted by the aucthoritie aforesaied, that if the partie, so hereafter to be outlawed, shal within one yere next after thesaied outlawrie, pronounced or Iudgement geuen vpon the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saied outlawrie, yelde hymself vnto the chief Iustice of Englande, for the tyme beyng, and offer to trauers the endictement, or appele, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon thesaied outlawrie shalbe pronounced, as is aforesaid, that then he shalbe receiued to thesaid trauerse, and beyng thereupon found not giltie, by the verdict of .xii. men, he shalbe clerely acquited, and dischar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged of thesaied outlawrie, and of all penalties and forfeictures, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of thesame, in as large and ample maner and forme, as though no suche outlawrie had been made, any thyng herein conteined, to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary in any wise, notwithstandyng.</p>
            <p>And bee it further enacted, by the aucthoritie aforesaied, that euery offendour, and offendours, beeyng hereafter lawfully conuicte, of any
<pb facs="tcp:150874:21"/> maner of high Treason, by presentment, confession, verdict, or processe of outlawrie, accordyng to the due course, and custome of the lawes of this Realme, shall lose, and forfeicte to the Kynges highnes, his heires and successours aforesaied, all suche landes, tenementes, and heredita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, whiche any suche offendour, or offendours, shall haue, of any estate of enheritaunce, in his awne right, in vse, or possessiō, within this realme of Englande, or els where, within any the Kynges dominions, at the tyme of any suche treasons committed, or at any tyme after.</p>
            <p>And it is further enacted, by the aucthoritie aforesaid, that no per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, or persones, shal in any wise be empeched, for any of the offences a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue saied committed onely by open preachyng, or woordes, onles the offendour, or offendours, be therof accused, within thre monethes next after thesame open preachyng, or wordes, and that thesame accusaciō, or accusacions, be had, made, and declared, to one of the kynges coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saill, or to one of the kynges Iustices of Assise, or els to one of the kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges Iustices of the peace, beyng of the <hi>Quorum,</hi> or to two Iustices of the Peace, within the Shiere, where thesame offence, or offences, shall happen to be dooen, or committed, any thyng conteined in this acte, to the contrary thereof in any wise, notwithstandyng.</p>
            <p>Prouided also, and be it declared, and enacted, by thaucthoritie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresaid, that concelement, or kepyng secret of any high treason, be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and taken, onely misprison of treason, and thoffendor therin, to for feict and suffer, as in cases of misprision of treason, as heretofore hath been vsed, any thyng aboue mencioned to the cōtrary, notwithstādyng</p>
            <p>Prouided alwaies, &amp; be it enacted by thaucthoritie aforesaied, that no persone, or persones, after the first daie of Iune next commyng, shal be endicted, arreigned, condempned, conuicted, or attamted, for any of the treasons, or offences aforesaied, or for any other treasons, that now be, or hereafter shalbe, whiche shall hereafter be perpetrated, commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, or doen, onles thesame offendour, or offendours, be thereof accused by twoo lawfull accusets, whiche saied accusers, at the tyme of the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reignement of the partie accused, if thei be then liuyng, shalbe brought in persone before the partie so accused, and auowe and maintein that, that thei haue to saie against thesaid partie, to proue hym giltie of the treasons, or offences conteined in the bill of endictment laied against the partie arreigned, onles thesaied partie arreigned shall willyngly without violence confesse thesame. Sauyng to euery persone, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sones, their heires and successors, other then the offendours, and their heires, and suche persone, and persones, as claime to any their vses, all suche rightes, titles, interest, possessions, leases, rentes, reuersions, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, and other profites, whiche thei, or any of theim shall haue, at the daie of committyng suche Treasons, or at any tyme after, in as large and ample maner, as if this acte had neuer been had, nor made.</p>
            <p>Prouided also, and be it enacted by thaucthoritie aforsaid, that the
<pb n="xx" facs="tcp:150874:21"/> wife, or wiues, whose husbāde, or husbādes, herafter shalbe atteinted of treasons specified in this acte, or of any other treasons whatsoeuer thei be, shal in no wise be receiued, to aske chalenge, demaunde, or haue dowry, of any the landes, tenemētes, or hereditamētes, of any the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sone, or persones, to be attainted of treason, as is aforesaid, during thesaide atteindonr in his force, any thing before mencioned to the contra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry in any wyse notwithstandyng.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="12" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ The .xii. Chapiter. ¶ An acte, for the declaration of a statute, made for the mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age of priestes, and for the legitimation of their children,</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lbeit, that at the Session of this parlament, holdē by prorogation at Westminster, the .iiii. day of No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uembre, in the second yere of the reigne of the Kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges Maiestie that now is, it was ordeined &amp; enac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by thaucthoritie of thesame parlament, that all and euery lawe, and lawes positiue, Canones, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitucions and ordinaūces, before that made, by the aucthoritie of man onely, whiche then bid prohibite and forbid mariage to any ecclesiasticall, and spiritual persone, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, of what estate, cōdiciō, or degree, thei then wer, or by what name or names so euer they then wer called, whiche by gods law might law fully mary, and all and euery article, braunche, &amp; sentence, concernyng onely the prohibicion for the mariage of the persones aforesaid, should be vtterly voide, and of none effect: And that al maner of forfeictures, paines, penalties, crimes, or actions, whiche wer in thesaid lawes con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teined, or of thesame did folow, concerning the prohibition for the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage of the persones aforesaide, shoulde be clerelye and vtterly voide, frustrate, and of none effect, to all ententes, constructions and purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, aswel cōcernyng mariage afore that tyme made by any of the Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiastical, or spiritual persones aforesaid, as also suche, whiche there after should be duely and lawfully had, celebrated, and made, betwixte the persones whiche by the lawes of God mighte lawfully marie. Yet sence the making of thesaide acte, duiers euell disposed persones, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersely takyng occasion, of certeine wordes, and sentences, in thesame acte comprised, haue, and do vntruly, and very slaunderously report of priestes Matrimonie saieng, that thesame statute is but a permission of Priestes Matrimonie, as vsurie, and other vnlawfull thynges bee now permitted, for theschuyng of greatter inconucnience, &amp; euilles, so that thereby the lawfull Matrimony of priestes in the opinion of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and the children procreate, and borne in suche lawful Matrimonie rather be of a great nombre of the kinges subiectes, accompted as ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stardes, then lawfully borne, to the greate slaunder perill, and disheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of suche children. Whiche vntrue slaunderous reproche of holy ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimony, doth not onely redounde to the highe dishonour of almightye
<pb facs="tcp:150874:22"/> God, but also to the kynges maiesties dishonor, and his high courte of parlament and the learned clergie of this Realme, who haue determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned thesame to be most lawful, by the lawe of God, in theire conuoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion, aswel by their common assent, as by the subscription of their han<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des. And that most of al is to be lamented, throughe suche vncomelye railynges of matrimony, and slaunderous reproches of the clergye, the word of God is not heard with reuerence, folowed with diligence, the godly procedynges of the kynges maiestie, not receiued with due obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, and therby the welthy men of this realme discouraged, to nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rishe and bring vp their children in learning, so as it is to be feared, lest in place of good learnyng and knowledge, shall crepe in ignoraunce, and for learned men, vnlearned ambicious men, and staterers, to the great displeasure of almighty god, &amp; to the perill of the whole state of Gods true religiō, within this realme, if spedy remedy be not prouided herin.</p>
            <p>Therfore it is enacted, by the kyng our souereigne Lorde, with the assent of the lordes, spiritual and temporall, and the commons in thys present Parlament assembled, and by thaucthoritie of thesame parla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that the Matrimony of al, and euery priest, and other Ecclesia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sticall, and spirituall persones, and persone, heretofore had, celebrated, and made, and the matrimony of euery priest, and other Ecclesiasticall and spirituall persone, whiche shall hereafter duelye be had, celebrated and made, shalbe adiuged, demed and taken, for true, iust, and lawfull Matrimony, to al ententes, constructions, and purposes. And that all and euery children, and childe, borne in any suche Matrimony, shalbee demed, iudged, reputed, and taken, to al ententes, constructions, and purposes to be borne in lawful matrimony, and to be legittimate, and enheritable to landes, tenementes, and other hereditamentes, from, &amp; by any of their fathers, mothers, and other auncestours, in like maner and fourme, to all ententes, constructions, and purposes, as any other children, borne in lawful Matrimony, betwixt any of the kynges laie subiectes be enheritable, and that by the aucthoritie aforesaide, aswel al and euery priest, and other Ecclesiasticall, and spirituall person, and persons, be, and shalbe enhabled to be tenauntes, by the courtesie, after the death of their wiues, of all suche landes, tenementes, and other he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reditamentes, as their wiues shall happē to be seised of, of estate in fee simple, or estate in fee taile general, duryng the espousails, as also eue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry wife, of euery suche priest, and other Ecclesiasticall persone, shalbe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabled to claime, demaunde, haue and enioy dower, of the landes, tene<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mentes, and other hereditamentes, whereof her husbande, during the espousailles betwene them, was seised of estate in fee Simple, or Fee taile generall in his awne right, in lyke maner and fourme, to al enten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, constructions, and purposes, as any other husbande, or wife, maye or might, claime, demaunde, haue or enioy. Any Lawe, Statute, orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce, Canon, constitucion, prescription, or custome, had, made, exerci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sed
<pb n="xxi" facs="tcp:150874:22"/> or vsed in this tealme to the contrary in any wise, notwithstādyng.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwaie, that this Acte, nor any thyng therein conteined, shall extende to geue libertie to any persone to matie, without askyng in the Churche, or without the Ceremonies, accordyng to the Boke of Common praier, &amp; administracion of the sacramentes, nor shall make any suche matrimonie alredy made, or hereafter to be made, good, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che are prohibited by the lawe of God for any other cause.</p>
            <p>Prouided also that this acte, nor any thyng therin conteined, shall extende to alter, chaunge, reuoke, repeale, or other wise to disanull any decree, iudgement, or sentence of diuorce, heretofore had or made, or to chaunge or alter, the possession or enheritaunce, of any landes or tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, alredy descended, but that thei and euery of them, shall remain continue, and be of suche like force, effect, strength and degree, to all en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentes, construccions and purposes, as thei were before the makyng of this acte. This Acte, or any thyng therein conteined to the contrary in any wise, notwithstandyng.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="13" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ The .xiii. Chapiter. ¶ An Acte, for the declaracion of a statute, made in the .xxxi. yere of Kyng Henry the eight, touchyng Religious persones.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here by an Acte of Parlament, made in the .xxxi. yere of the reigne of the moste noble Prince, of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous memorie, kyng Henry theight, for, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernyng the enablemēt of professed, and religious persones, to purchase to them, and to their heires, in fee simple, fee tatle, for terme of life, for yeres, or at will: manours, landes, tenementes, tentes, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuities, and other hereditamentes, and thynges whatsoeuer: And that thei, and euery of theim, should or might, from thencefurthe vse, and exercise, receiue, take, haue, and enioye, all, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery lawfull thyng, and thynges, to bee growen, fallen, or happened to them, or any of them, after thesame decraiment, or departyng out of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. And in whiche said acte of Parlament, there is a prouiso contei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, that none of thesame teligious persones should, or might, at any tyme after the makyng of thesame Acte, bee taken, demed, or iudged, for, or as heire, or heires, or enheritable to any persone, or persones, to any purpose, respect, construccion, or entent in the lawe, as by thesame acte, emong other thynges therin conteined, more fully at large it may and doth appere. And forasmuche as sithe the tyme of the makyng of thesaid acte, there hath been certain ambiguities and doubtes, growen and arisen, and hereafter are like to growe, and arise, vpon the exposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of thesaid acte, whether thesaied late teligious, and professed per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sones should, or might be adiudged, able to enherite, and to be enheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, as heire, or heires, to any of his, or their auncestour, or aunce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stours,
<pb facs="tcp:150874:23"/> and to haue, and enioye, all, and euery thyng, and thynges, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scended, growen, fallen, or happened, to them, or any of them, after the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saied deraiment, or departyng out of Religion, yea; or no. For the full and plain declaracion whereof, be it enacted, declared, and expounded, by the aucthoritie of this present Parlament, and by the aucthoritie of thesame, that all, and euery of thesame late Religious, and professed persone, and persones, shall, and maie, by aucthoritie of this Acte, bee enabled, to all ententes, construccions, and purposes, at all tyme, and tymes hereafter, to be taken, demed, and iudged, as heire, or heires, and enheritable to all, and euery their auncestour, or auncestours, and to haue, chalenge, enioye, receiue, and take, all manours, landes, tenemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, and Hereditamentes, and euery other thyng, and thynges, to them or any of them, fallen, come, growen, or descended, from any their aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cestours, by any maner of waies, sence the tyme of their seuerall derai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, or departyng out of their religion, in as ample and large ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, fourme, and condicion, as thei had neuer been professed, nor ente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into Religion, thesame profession, or Religion, or any Lawe, cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stome, or vse, within this Realme to the contrary thereof in any wise, notwithstandyng.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwaies, and be it further enacted, by thaucthoritie afor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saied, that none of thesaied religious persones, shall, or maie, by vertue of this acte, at any tyme hereafter, be taken, demed, or iudged for heire, or heires, or enheritable to any persone, or persones, to any construcci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or entent in the Lawe, by reason of any former right, title, enterest, matter, or cause, had, made, doen, descended, or growen, to any respecte or purpose, before their saied seuerall detaimentes, or departyng out of their Religion, any thyng before in this Acte, or in thesaied former acte conteined to the contrary hereof in any wise, notwithstandyng.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="14" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ The .xiiii. Chapiter. ¶ An acte, against Regratours, Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stallers, and Engrossers.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lbeit, diuerse good statutes, heretofore haue been made, against forestallers of Met chaundises, and victualles, yet for that good lawes, and statutes, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst regratours, and engrossers of thesame thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, haue not been heretofore sufficiently made, and prouided, and also for that it hath not been perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly knowen, what person should be taken for a fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>staller, Regratour, or Engrosser, thesaied statutes, haue not taken good effecte, accordyng to the myndes of the makers therof: therfore, be it enacted and declared, by the kyng our souereigne lorde, with thassent of the lordes spirituall and temporall, and the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, in this present Parlament assembled, and by the aucthoritie of thesame: that whatsoeuer persone, or persones, that after the first daie
<pb n="xxij" facs="tcp:150874:23"/> of Maie nexte commyng, shall buye, or cause to be bought, any Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaundise, victuall, or any other thyng whatsoeuer, commyng by land or by water, toward any Market, or Faier, to be sold in thesame, or cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myng toward any Citee, Port, Hauen, Cricke, or Rode, of this realme, or Wales, from any parte beyond the sea, to be sold, or make any bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, contract, or promise, for the hauyng, or buiyng of thesame, or any part therof, so commyng, as is aforesaied, before thesaied Merchaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dise, victualles, or other thyng, shalbee in the Markette, Faier, Citee, Port, Hauen, Cricke, or Rode, redy to be sold: or shall make any mociō by woorde, letter, message, or otherwise, to any persone, or persones, for thenhauncyng of the price, or derer sellyng of any thyng, or thynges, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue mencioned, or els diswade, moue, or stirre, any person, or persones commyng to the Market, or Faier, to abstein, or forbeare, to bryng, or conueigh, any of the thynges aboue rehersed, to any Markette, Faier, Citee, Port, Hauen, Cricke, or Rode, to be sold, as is aforesaied, shal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be demed, taken, and adiudged, for a Forestaller.</p>
            <p>Further bee it enacted, and declared, by the aucthoritie aforesaied, that whatsoeuer persone, or persones, that after thesaied firste daie or Maie, shall by any meanes regrate, obtain, or get, into his, or their hā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, or possession, in any Faier, or Markette, any Corne, Wine, Fishe, Butter, Chese, Candelles, Tallowe, Shepe, Lambes, Calues, Swine Pigges, Giese, Capons, Hennes, Chekins, Pigeons, Comes, or other ded victuall whatsoeuer, that shalbe brought to any Faier, or Market within this realme, or Wales, to be solde, and do sell thesame again in any Faier, or Market, holden, or kept in thesame place, or in any other Faier, or Market, within foure miles thereof, shalbe accepted, reputed and taken, for a Regratour, or Regratours.</p>
            <p>And be it also enacted, and declared, by the aucthoritie aforesaied, that whatsoeuer persone, or persones, that after thesaied firste daie of Maie, shall engrosse, or gette, into his, or their handes, by buiyng, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractyng, or promise takyng, other then by demise, graunt, or Lease of lande, or tithe: any corne, growyng in the fieldes, or any other corne, or Grain, Butter, Chese, Fishe, or other ded victualles whatsoeuer, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the realme of Englande, to thentent to sell thesame again, shalbe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, reputed, and taken, an vnlawfull Engrosser, or Engrossers.</p>
            <p>And if any persone, or persones, shall at any tyme, after thesaid first daie of Maie, offende in any of the thynges before recited, and beeyng therof duely conuicted, or attainted, by the lawes of this realme, or af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the fourme hereafter mencioned: shall for his, or their firste offence, haue, and suffer imprisonment, by the space of two monethes, without baile, or mainprise, and shall also lose, and forfeicte the value of the goodes, cattell, and victuall, so by hym, or them bought, or had.</p>
            <p>And if any persone, lawfully conuicted, or attainted, of, or for any the offences aboue saied, bee thereof eftsones lawfully conuicted, or at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teinted,
<pb facs="tcp:150874:24"/> that then euery persone, or persones so offendyng, shall haue, and suffer, for his saied seconde offence, imprisonement by the space of one haulfe yere, without baile, or mainprise, and shall lose the double value of all the goodes, cattell, and victuall, so by hym bought, or had, as is aforesaied.</p>
            <p>And if any persone beyng lawfully twise conuicted, or attainted, of, or for any of thesaied offences, shall eftsones offende the thirde tyme, and bee thereof lawfully conuicted, or attainted, that then euery suche persone, for thesaid third offence, shalbe set on the pillourie in the citee, toune, or place, where he shall then dwell, and enhabite, and lose, and forfeicte all the goodes, and cattell, that he, or thei, haue to their awne vse, and also be committed to prison, there to remain, duryng the Kynges Maiesties pleasure.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwaie, and it is enacted and declared, by thaucthoritie aforesaid, that the buiyng of any suche barley, Bigge, or Otes, as any persone, or persones (not forestallyng) shall buye, to conuert into malt, or otemeale, in his, or their awne house, or houses, and so shalbe conuet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in deede, or the buiyng of any suche thyng, by any suche Fishemon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, Boucher, or Pulter, as concerne his, or their awne facultie, crafte, or Misterie (otherwise then by forestallyng) whiche shall sell thesame again vpon reasonable prices by retaill, or the takyng of any cattell, corne, grain, butter, chese, or any other thyng aboue mēcioned, reserued without fraude, or couin, vpon any lease for terme of life, or lifes, yere, or yeres, heretofore made, or hereafter to be made: or the buiyng of any wine, or other dedde victuall aboue mencioned, beeyng apte and mete for mannes sustenaunce, by any Inneholder, or other victualler, to sell thesame by retail within his house, or to any of his neighbors for their sustenaunce, for reasonable prices, or the buiyng of any dried, or salted fishe, herryng, or sprottes (not forestalled) and sold for reasonable pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, or the buiyng of any corne, fishe, butter, or chese, by any suche bad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, lader, kiddier, or carier, as shalbe assigned, and allowed to that of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, or doyng, by three Iustices of Peace, of the countrie, where thesaid badger, lader, kidder, or carier shall dwell, whiche shall sell, or deliuer in open Faier, or market, or to any other victualler, or to any other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sone, or persones, for the prouision of his, or their house, or houses, all suche corne, grain, butter, and chese, as any suche persone shall buye, or cause to be bought (and that within one moneth, nexte after he shall so buye any suche Corne, Grain, Butter, or Chese) so that thesame shalbe bought without forestallyng: or els that any common prouision made or hereafter to be made, without fraude or couin, by any person, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sones, of any of the thynges abouesaid, for any citee, borough, or toune corporate, or for prouision of victuallyng of any ship, Castle, or Forte, within the kynges dominiōs, without forestallyng, whiche shalbe em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed onely to that vse, and purpose: Or the buiyng and prouision of
<pb n="xxiij" facs="tcp:150874:24"/> any of the victualles aboue mencioned, necessarye, and requisite for the furniture and prouision of the enhabitauntes of Calais, Guisnes, and other the Marches of thesame, or of the toune of Barwicke, Holly I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slande, or the Marches of Englande against Scotlande, whiche with out fraude, or couine shalbe transported, &amp; conueighed, assone as wind and wether may serue, to suche of the places aforesaide, for the whiche thesame shalbe so prouided, shall not be in any wise demed, adiudged, or taken any offence contrary to this acte.</p>
            <p>And it is also further enacted, by the aucthoritie aforesaide, that if any persone, or persones, after thesaide firste day of Maye nexte com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myng, hauyng sufficiente Corne, and graine for the prouision of his, or their owne house, or houses, and sowyng of their groūdes, for one yere doe buye any corne in any Faier, or Market, for the chaunge of hys, or their sede, and do not bring to thesame Faier, or Market, thesame day so muche corne, as he shal fortune to buye for his sede, and sel thesame, if he can, as the price of corne then goeth in thesaid Market, or Faier: that then euery suche persone, or persons so buyeng corne for sede shal forfeicte and lose the double value of the corne so boughte. Or if any persone, or persones, aftre thesaide firste daye of Maye shall buye any maner of Oxen Roōtes, Stieres, Kine, Heckfers, Calues, Sheepe, lambes, goates, or kiddes liuyng, &amp; sel thesame againe aliue, onles he or they do kepe, &amp; fede thesame by the space of .v. wekes, in his, or their owne houses, ground, ferme groūd, or els in suche ground, or groūdes where he, or they haue the herbage, or common of pasture, by graunte, or prescription: that then euerry persone, or persones, so buieng and sel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyng againe shal lose the double value of the cattall, or thynges so bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ught and sold againe. The moitie of al whiche forfeitures afore reher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed shalbe to the kyng, and the other moitie to him, or theim, that wyll sue for thesame, in anye of the Kynges Courtes of Recorde, by Bille, plaint, action of debt, or enformation, in the whiche bill, plaint, action, or information, no wager of law, essoine, or protection shalbe admitted</p>
            <p>Bee it also further enacted, by the aucthoritie afore said, that the Iustices of the Peace in euery countie, within this realme, or Wales, at their quartre Sessions, shall haue ful power and aucthoritie by ver<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tue of this acte, to enquire, heare, and determine, all, and euery the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faultes and offences perpetrated, committed, or doone, contrarye to this acte, within the countie, where any suche sessions shalbe kepte, by inquisition, presentmente, bill, or enformation before theim exhibited, and by examination of twoo lawfull witnesses, or by anye of thesame waies, or meanes, by the discretion of the saide Iustices, and to make processe therupon, as though they wer endicted before them by inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition, or by veredict of .xii. menne, or more: and vpō the conuiction of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> offendor, by information, or sute of any other then the Kynge, to make extractes of the one moitie of the forfeictures, to be leuied to the kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges
<pb facs="tcp:150874:25"/> vse, as they vse to do, of other fines, issues, and amerciamētes gro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wen in the Sessions of peace, and to award execution of thother moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie for the complainaunt, or enfourmer againste the offendour, by <hi>Fieri facias,</hi> or <hi>Capias,</hi> as the kinges Iustices at Westminster may do and vse to do. And if any suche conuiction, or attamdour, shal herafter happen to be at the kynges sure onely, that then the whole forfeictures to bee extracted and leuied to the Kynges vse onely.</p>
            <p>And it is further enacted, by thaucthoritie aforesaied, that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer personne, shall at any tyme hereafter, bee punished by vertue of this acte, for any thyng mencioned in this acte, that then thesame per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sone shal not otherwyse be, vexed, troubled, sued, or put to any paine, or punishment for that thyng, wherefore he, or they shal haue bene so pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwayes, and it is enacted by the aucthoritie aforesaide that it shalbe lawful to any persone, or personnes, whiche shalbe assi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gned, and allowed by thre Iustices of the peace, of the Countie where he shall dwelle, therunto, to buye, (otherwise then by forstallyng) corne graine, or cattall, to be transported, or caried by water from any porte or place within this realme, or Wales, vnto any other Porte, or place, within thesaide realme, or dominions, if he, or they shal without fraud or couine, shippe, or embarke within .lx. dayes next after he, or theie shal haue boughte thesame, or taken couenaunte, or promise for the buyeng thereof, and with suche expedicion, and diligence, as wynde, and wether will serue, to carye and transporte thesame to suche Porte, or place, as his, or their cockettes shal declare, and there dooe disbarke, vnlade, and sel thesame, and do bryng a true certificat thereof, from one Iustice of peace of the countie, or Mayor, or Bailife of the toune corporate wher thesame shalbe vnladen, and also of the Customer of the Porte, where suche vnladyng shalbe: of the place, and daye, where thesaide Corne, or cattal shalbe disbarked, vnladen, and solde, to be directed vnto the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stomer, and Comptroller of the porte, where thesame ware embarked, any thing mencioned in this acte to the contrary, notwithstandyng.</p>
            <p>And ouer that, that at al times hereafter, when wheate shalbe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monlye at the price, of .vi. s̄ .viij. đ. the Quarter, or vnder, Malte, and Barley, at .iii. s̄ .iiii. đ. the Quarter, or vnder, Otes, or Otes malted, at the price of ii. s̄. the quarter, or vnder, Pease, or Beanes, at the price of iiij. s̄. the quarter, or vnder, and Rie, or Misseleine, at the price of .v. s̄. the quarter, or vnder (al whiche quarters shalbe entended to be of Lon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>don measure,) that then it shalbe lawful to euery persone, and persones (not forstallyng) to buy, engrosse, and kepe, in his, or their Graneries, or houses, suche Corne of the kyndes aforesaide, as wythout fraud, or couine shalbe bought, at, or vnder the prices afore expressed, any thing in this acte to the contrary notwithstanding.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwayes, and be it enacted, by thaucthoritie aforesaide,
<pb n="xxiiij" facs="tcp:150874:25"/> that this acte, or any thyng therein conteined, extend not to charge any persone, or persones, for any the offences aboue mencioned, onles he, or thei be sued for thesame, within. it yeres next after suche offence doen or committed. This acte to endure vntill the ende of the next Parlament.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwaies, and be it enacted by the aucthoritie aforesaied, that it shalbe lawfull to all, and euery of the kynges Maiesties subie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctes, now dwellyng, and enhabityng, or that hereafter shall dwell, or enhabite within one mile of the maigne sea, to buie all maner of Fishe, freshe, or salted (not forestallyng thesame) and to sell thesame again at reasonable prices: this acte, or any thyng therein conteined to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary in any wise, notwithstandyng.</p>
            <p>Prouided also, and be it enacted by the aucthoritie aforesaied, that it shalbe lawfull to all, and euery persone, and persones, knowen for a cōmon Drouer, or Drouers, beyng licenced, aucthorised, and allowed in writyng, by three Iustices of the Peace (whereof one to bee of the <hi>Quorum)</hi> of the Countie, or Counties, where thesame Drouer, or Dro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, shalbe moste abidyng, &amp; dwellyng, to buye cattell in suche shires, or counties, where Drouers haue been wont in times past accustoma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly to buie cattell, at their free libertie and pleasure, and to sell thesame as is aforesaied, at reasonable prices, in common Faiers, and Market<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, distant from the place, or places, where he, or thei shall buye the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>same .xl. miles at the least, so that thesame cattel be not bought by way of forestallyng. This Acte, or any thyng therein conteined to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary in any wise, notwithstandyng.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwaies, that suche licence of Iustices of the Peace, shal not endure aboue one yere, onles thesame be yerely renewed by so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Iustices, as is aforesaied.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="15" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ The .xv. Chapiter. ¶ An acte, against regratours of Tanned Lether.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here, by the couetousnes of diuerse gredye perso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, regratyng and engrossyng, al kynd of tanned lether into their hādes, and sellyng again thesame at excessiue prices, to Sadlers, Girdlers, Corde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wainers, and suche other artificers, and hādicraf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes men, as make wares of tanned lether, the kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges louyng subiectes are enforced to buie thesaid wares, at vnreasonable prices, for remedy and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formacion whereof: Be it enacted by the kyng our souercigne Lorde, with thassent of the Lordes, Spirituall and Temporall, and the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons in this present Parlament assembled, and by the aucthoritie of thesame, that from, and after the first daie of Maie next commyng, no persone, or persones, of what estate, degree, or condicion, soeuer he, or thei bee, shall buie, or engrosse, or cause to be bought, or engrossed, any
<pb facs="tcp:150874:26"/> kynde of Tanned Lether, to thentent to sell thesame again, vpon pain to forfeict thesaied Lether so bought, or the iust price thereof. The one moytie of whiche forfeicture, shalbe to the kyng our souereigne lorde, and the other moytie to him, or them, that shall lease, or sue for thesame in any of the kynges courtes of record, by accion of debt, bill, plaint, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formacion, or otherwise, wherein no wager of lawe, essoyne, proteccion, or Iniunccion shalbe admitted, or allowed for the defendaunt.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwaie, and be it enacted, by thaucthoritie aforesaid, that all Sadlers, Girdlers, Cordewainers, and al other artificers, suche as make males, Bougettes, Lether pottes, Tanckardes, bare hides, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other wares of Lether, shall, or maie buy, all suche kynd of Tanned lether, as is, or shalbe necessary for their occupiyng, to be wrought and made by them, or by their seruauntes, in, or about their said wares, any thyng before mencioned in this acte to the contrary, notwithstandyng.</p>
            <p>Prouided also, that euery Girdler, and other artificer before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cioned in this Acte, maie at his free will and pleasure, sell their neckes, wombes, and shreddes of Tanned Lether (suche as thei, or any of them cannot occupie, aboute the wares thei vse to make) to any persone, or persones, without incurryng any forfeicte, pain, or penaltie before ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed in this Acte, any thyng herein conteined to the contrary, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstandyng.</p>
            <p>Prouided also, and bee it further enacted, by the aucthoritie afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said, that it shalbe lawfull, to, or for, euery persone, or persones, whiche now haue, or hereafter shall haue, the kynges maiesties speciall licence or licences, to transporte, cary, or conueigh ouer the seas, any kynde of Tanned Lether, to buie for the furniture of their saied licence, or licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, in open Faier, or Market, suche, and so muche Tanned Lether, as he, or thei be, or shalbe licensed to transport, cary, or conueigh. So that thesame licence, or licences, be presented, and shewed, vnto the chief of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer, or officers, that now haue, or hereafter shall haue, the gouernaūce of any Citee, Toune Faier, or Market, whereas thesaid Lether, or any part thereof, shalbe bought. And so that thesaied officer, or officers, se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng thesame licence to be good, and perfecte, do iustly, and truely write vpon the backside of euery suche licence, or licences, how muche Tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned lether, he or thei, shall there haue bought, and the certain daie, time and place of buiyng thesame, that thereby it maie manifestly appere, how, and when, euery suche licence, or licences, be, or shalbe satisfied, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thyng in this acte to the contrary, notwithstandyng.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted, by the aucthoritie abouesaied, that after thesaid first daie of Maie next commyng, no persone, or persones, shall shippe, or cause to bee shipped (to the entent to cary, transporte, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueigh ouer the seas, as Marchaundise to be sold, or exchaunged there) any Shoes, Bootes, Buskins, Stertuppes, or Slippers, vpon pain to forfeict all, and euery suche Shoes, Bootes, Buskins, Stertuppes
<pb n="xxv" facs="tcp:150874:26"/> or Slippers. so shipped, contrarie to the true meanyng of this Acte, or the value of thesame. The one moietie of thesaid forfeicture to be to the Kyng our souereigne Lord, and the other moietie to hym, or them, that shal sease, or sewe for thesame, in any of the Kynges Maiesties courtes of recorde, by action of debte, bille, plainte, enformacion, or otherwyse. Wherin no wager of lawe, essome, protection, or iniunction shalbe ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, or allowed for the defendaunt.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwaies, and be it enacted by thaucthoritie aforesaid, that this Acte, ne any thyng therin conteined, shall not in any wyse extende to be preiudicial, or hurtfull to any person, or persons, beyng the Kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges subiectes, for transportyng or carieng ouer the Seas vnto Calice, or the marches of the same, and vnto the Isle of man, so muche, or as many of the afore said made wares (as Bootes, Buskyns, Stertup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes, and Slippers heretofore recited) as shalbe necessarie and conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient for the wearyng, and furniture of the Kynges subiectes in them, or any of them. Any thyng in this last Acte conteined to the contrarie hereof in any wyse, notwithstandyng.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwaies, and be it enacted by thaucthoritie aforesaid, that no Sadler, Girdler, Cordwainer, nor other artificer, dwellyng within the citie of London, and the suburbes of the same, whiche shal cutte the same tanned leather, (as is aforesaid to thentēt to make wares therof) shal courrie, or dresse, any of the foresaid tanned leather, in his, or their owne house, or houses, or by his, or their seruaunt, or seruauntes, vpon paine of forfeicture, al, and euery thesaid tanned leather, so to be cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried. The one moietie of whiche forfeicture shalbe to our souereigne Lorde the Kyng, and the other moietie to the partie that wil sue for the same, in any of the Kynges courtes of recorde, by Bille, Plainte, Actiō or enformacion. Wherin no wager of lawe, essome protection, or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunction, shalbe admitted, or allowed for the defendaunt.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="16" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ The .xvi. Chapiter. ❧ An Acte against buyeng, and sellyng of Offices.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>OR the auoidyng of corruption, whiche may here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after happen to be in the officers, and ministers, in those courtes, places, or roumes, wherin there is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quisite to be had the true administracion of iustice, or seruices of truste, and to thentent that persones worthie, &amp; mete to be aduaunced to the place where iustice is to be ministred, or any seruice of trust exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted, shoulde hereafter be preferred to thesame, and no other:</p>
            <p>Be it therfore enacted, by the Kyng our souereigne Lord, the lordes Spiritual, &amp; Temporal, and the commons in this present Parlament assembled, and by thaucthoritie of the same: That if any person, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons
<pb facs="tcp:150874:27"/> at any time hereafter, bargaine, or selle any office, or offices, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putacion of any office, or offices, or any parte, or parcel of any of them, or receiue, haue, or take any money, fee, rewaide, or any other profet directly, or indirectly, or take any promise, agrement, couenaunt, bond, or any assuraunce, to receiue, or haue any money, fee, rewarde, or other profite directly, or indirectly, for any office, or offices, or for the deputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of any office, or offices, or any parte of any of them, or to thentent that any person shoulde haue, exercise, or enioye any office, or offices, or the deputacion of any office, or offices, or any parte of any of them, whiche office, or offices, or any parte, or parcel of them, shal in any wise touche, or concerne thadministracion, or execution of iustice, or the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipte, comptrolement, or paiment of any the Kynges highnes trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soure, money, rente, reuenue, accompte, alneage, auditourshippe, or sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueieng of any the Kynges Maiesties honoures, Castelles, Manours, Landes, tenementes, woodes, or hereditamentes, or any the Kynges Maiesties customes, or any administracion, or necessarie attendaunce to be had, doen, or executed in any the Kynges maiesties custome house, or houses, or the kepyng of any the Kynges Maiesties Townes, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stelles, or fortresses, beyng vsed, occupied, or appointed for a place of strengthe, and defence, or whiche shal concerne, or touche any clerke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shippe to be occupied in any maner of Courte of recorde, wherin iusti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce is to be ministred, that then all and euery suche person, and persons, that shall so bargaine, or selle any of thesaid office, or offices, deputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion, or deputacions, or that shall take any money, fee, rewarde, or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite for any of thesaid office, or offices, deputacion, or deputacions of any of thesaid offices, or any parte of any of them, or that shall take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny promise, couenaunte, bonde, or assuraunce for any money, rewarde, or profite to be geuen for any of thesaid office, or offices, deputacion, or deputacions, of any of thesaid office, or offices, or any parte, of any of them, shall not onely lose, and forfeicte all his, and their right, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest and estate, whiche suche person, or persones shall then haue, of, in, or to, any of thesaid office, or offices, deputacion, or deputacions, or any parte, of any of them, or of, in, or to, the gifte, or nominacion of any of thesaid office, or offices, deputacion, or deputacions, for the whiche office, or offices, or for the deputacion, or deputacions, of whiche office, or offices, or for any parte of any of them, any suche person, or persones, shall so make any bargaine, or sale, or take, or receiue any somme of money, fee, rewarde, or profite, or any promise, couenaunt, or assuraunce to haue, or receiue any fee, rewarde, money, or profite: But also that all, and euery suche person, and persones that shall geue, or paie any somme of money, rewarde, or fee, or shall make any promyse, agremente, bonde, or assuraunce for any of thesaid of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, or for the deputacion, or deputacions, of any of thesaid office, or offices, or any parte of any of them, shall immediatly by and vpon
<pb n="xxvi" facs="tcp:150874:27"/> thesame fee, money, or rewarde, geuen, or paied, or vpon any suche pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise, couenaunt, bonde, or agrement, had, or made, for any fee, sōme of money, or rewarde to be paied, as is aforesaide, be adiudged a disabled persone in the law, to al ententes, and purposes, to haue, occupie, or en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy thesaid office, or offices, deputacion, or deputacions, or any parte of any of them, for the whiche suche persone, or persones, shall so geue, or paie, any some of money, fee, or reward, or make any promise, couenaūt bonde, or other assuraunce, to geue, or paie, any sōme of money, fee, or rewarde.</p>
            <p>And be it also enacted, by thaucthoritie aforesaide, that al, and eue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry suche bargaines, sales, promises, bondes, agrementes, couenauntes and assurances, as be before specified, shalbe voide, to and against him and them, by whome any suche bargaine, sale, bonde, promise, couena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unt, or assuraunce, shalbe had, or made.</p>
            <p>Prouided alway, that this acte, or any thyng therin conteined, shal not in any wise extende, to any office, or offices, wherof any persone, or persones, is or shalbe seased, of any estate of enheritaunce, nor to any Office of parkershippe, or of the kepyng of any Parke, house, manour, garden, chase, or forrest, or to any of them, any thyng in this acte here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore mencioned, to the contrary thereof in any wise, notwithstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</p>
            <p>Prouided also, that if any persone, or persones, do hereafter offende in any thing contrary to the tenour, &amp; effect of this acte, yet that not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding, al iudgementes geuen, and al other acte, and actes, exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted, or done, by any suche persone, or persones, so offendyng, by auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, or colour of the office, or deputacion, which ought to be forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, or not occupied, or not enioyed by the persone, so offending as is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresaid, after thesaid offence so by suche person committed, or done, &amp; before suche person so offending, for thesame offence be remoued from the exercise, administration, and occupation of thesaide office, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putacion, shalbee, and remaine, good, and sufficiente in Lawe, to al en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentes, cōstructions, and purposes, in suche lyke maner and fourme, as thesame should, and ought to haue remained, and bene, if this acte, had neuer bene hadde or made.</p>
            <p>Prouided also that this acte, or any thyng therin conteined, shal not in any wise extende, to any bargaine, sale, gifte, graunt nominacion, bonde, conenaunt, promise, agrement, or assuraunce whatsoeuer it be, of, or for any the office, or offices, deputacion, or deputacions aforesaid or any parte of any of theim, had made, done, concluded, or agreed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the firste daye of Marche nexte commyng, but that thesame bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, sale, gift, graunt, nominacion, bonde, couenaunt, promise, agre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente, or assuraunce, hadde, made, concluded, or agreed, before the saide firste daye of Marche, shall alwayes remaine, continue, and be in suche force, strengthe, and effecte, as if this Acte had neuer
<pb facs="tcp:150874:28"/> bene had, or made, any thing before in this acte mencioned to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary therof in any wise, notwithstanding.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwaies, and be it enacted by the aucthoritie aforesaide, that this Acte, or any thyng therein contemed, shal not in any wise ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tende, or be preiudiciall or hurtfull, to any of the chiefe Iustices of the Kynges Courtes, commonly called the Kynges Benche, or Common place, or to any of the Iustices of Assise, that now be, or hereafter shal be, but that they, and euery of theim, may dooe in euery behaulfe, tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chyng, or concernyng, any office or offices, to be geuen or graunted, by theim, or any of theim, as thei, or any of theim might haue doen, before the makyng of this Acte, any thing aboue mencioned to the contrary in any wise notwithstandyng.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="17" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ The .xvii. Chapiter. ¶ An Acte, for the continuaunce of certain Statutes.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HERE, in the Parlament begonne and holden at London, the thirde daie of Nouember, in the one and twenty yeare of the reigne, of our late moste drad so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uereigne lorde, of moste famous memorie, Kyng Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the eight, and from thence adiourned to West<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minster, and there holden and continued, by diuerse prorogacions, vnto the dissolucion thereof, one acte was made and established, for the restrainte of carieng, and conuei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghyng of Horses and Mares, out of this Realme. And also one other Acte was there made in thesaide Parlament, for the true makynge of Cables, Halsers, and Ropes: And also one other Acte was ther made for the true windynge of Wolles: And one other Acte, to restrain kyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge of wainlinges, Bullockes, Stieres, and Heickfers, beynge vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the age of twoo yeares, which sayde seuerall actes ware then ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de to endure, and continue, vnto the next Parlament, as by thesame thre seuerall Actes, more plainly appereth. And where also in thesame Parlament, one other acte was made and established, for atteintes to be sued, for the punishement of periurie, vpon vntrue verdictes: which acte last before rehersed, was then made and ordeined, to continue and endure, to the last daie of the next Parlament, as by thesame acte mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re plainly at large, is shewed and maie appere: And where also in the Parlamente, begon &amp; holden at Westminster, the .viij. daie of Iune, in the .xxviij. yeare of the reigne of our saide moste drad souereigne lorde, kyng Henry the .viij. and there continued &amp; kept, vntill the dissolucion therof, it was ordeined, &amp; enacted, that al &amp; singuler thesayde actes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue remembred, &amp; euery of thē, should cōtinue &amp; endure in their force
<pb n="xxvij" facs="tcp:150874:28"/> and strength, and also be obserued, and kepte, vntil the laste day of the nexte Parlament, as by the same Acte amonges other thynges therin conteined, more plainly appeteth:</p>
            <p>And where also in the Parlament begonne, and holden at West<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mynster the .xxviij. day of Aprill, in the .xxxi. yeare of the reigne of our said most drad souereigne Lorde Kyng Henry theight, and there conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued vntil the .xxviij. day of Iune, then nexte folowyng: It was ordei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and enacted by thaucthoritie of the same Parlament, that all, and singuler thesaid seuerall Actes aboue remembred, and euery of theim, and al clauses articles, and prouisions in them, and euery of them con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined, shoulde continue and endure in their force, and strength, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so be obserued, and kepte vntil the last day of the nexte Parlament, as by the same Acte amonges other thynges therin conteined, more plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appereth.</p>
            <p>And where also in the last Session of the same Parlament begonne at Westmynster the .xij. day of Aprill in thesaid .xxxi. yere of the reigne, of our said late souereigne Lorde, and there by diuers prorogacions continued, vntil the .xxiiij. day of Iuly, in the .xxxij. yere of our said late Souereigne Lorde, there was one other Acte made, and establisshed, concernyng buyeng of Fishe vpon the Sea: And also one other Acte was there made in thesaid Parlament for reasonable pryces of wynes to be sette, as by the same two Actes laste recited more plainly doeth appere:</p>
            <p>And where in the Parlament holden at Westmynster in the .xxxv. yere of the reigne of our said most drad souereigne Lorde Kyng Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry theight, one Acte was made for the preseruacion of wooddes, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure for .vij. yeres, then nexte folowyng, and from thence vnto thende of the nexte Parlament, as by the same Acte more plainly it doeth and may appere:</p>
            <p>And where also at the Parlament holden at Westmynster in the xxxvij. yere of the reigne of our said most drad souereigne Lorde Kyng Henry theight, and there continued, and kepte vntill the dissolucion therof: It was ordeined, and enacted, that all and singuler thesaid Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes aboue mencioned, and euery of them, except thesaid Acte made for the preseruacion of wooddes as is aforesaid, shoulde continue, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure in their force, and strengthe, and also be obserued, and kepte vntil the last day of the next Parlament, as by the same Acte amonges other thynges therein conteined, more plainly appereth:</p>
            <p>And where also in the Session of the Parlament holden at West<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mynster the .iiij. day of Nouember, in the thirde yeare of the reigne of our nowe most drad souereigne Lorde Kyng Edwarde the sixthe, one other Acte was made in the same Parlament against vnlawfull hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng in any parke, forrest, chase, or other enclosed grounde, whiche acte was then made to endure the space of thre ful yeres to be complete, and
<pb facs="tcp:150874:29"/> fully ended from the firste day of May then nexte commyng, as by the same Acte more plainly appereth. And for asmuche, as all and singuler thesaid seueral Actes aboue mencioned, be good and beneficial for the common wealth of this Realme:</p>
            <p>Be it therfore enacted, ordeined, and established by the Kyng our souereigne Lorde, with thassent of the Lordes Spirituall, and Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall, and the Commons in this present Parlament assembled, and by aucthoritie of the same, that all, and singuler thesaid seuerall Actes and Statutes aboue mencioned, or rehersed, and euery of them, and all Clauses, Articles, and prouisions in them, and euery of them con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined, and also all, and euery other braunche, article, and sentence conteined in thesaid Acte made in thesaid .xxxvii. yeare of thesaid late Kyng of most famous memorie Henry theight, touchyng, or in any wyse concernyng the settyng of prices of wyne, or the sale of the same, shall be reuiued, continued, stande, and endure in their force, and strengthe, to all ententes, constructions, and purposes, and shalbe ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serued, and kepte in all thynges vnto the last day of the nexte Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lament.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="18" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ The .xviii. Chapiter. ❧ An Acte repealyng a Statute made in the fourth yere of Kyng Henry the seuenth, against the bryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyng in of wyne, and woade in straunge bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomes.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HERE in the Parlament holden at Westmyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster the .xiii. day of Ianuary in the fourthe yere of the reigne of the famous Prynce, of worthie me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie, Kyng Henry the seuenth, aftre the conquest, grandfather to our nowe most gracious, and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural souereigne liege Lorde, it was amonges o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thynges ordeined, stablished, and enacted, that no maner of person, of what degree, or condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion that he ware, shoulde conuey, or brynge into this Realme, Irelande, Wales, Calais, or the marches therof, or Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wicke, from the feast of the Natiuitie of sainct Ihon Baptist that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that was in the yere of our Lorde God, a thousand, foure hundred, foure score, &amp; ten: any maner wynes growyng of the Duchie of Guyen or Gascoine, or woade, called Tholouse woade, but suche as shoulde be conueyed, auentured, and brought in shippe, or shippes, wherof the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said late Kyng, or some of his subiectes of this Realme of Englande, Irelande, Wales, Calaice, or Barwicke, ware owners, possessours, and proprietaries, and the maister vnder God, and the mariners of the
<pb n="xxviij" facs="tcp:150874:29"/> same shippe, or shippes, Englishe, Irishe, or Walshe, or men of Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wicke, or menne of Calaice, or of the marches of the same for the more partie, vpon paine to forfeicte the same wynes, or woade, so brought contrarie to thesaid Acte, as in thesaid Acte more at large it doeth and maie appere.</p>
            <p>The whiche Acte was supposed to be made for the maintenaunce of the nauoie of this Realme. And also to thentent, and vpon good hope, and trust to haue had the same wynes, and woade, at more easy pryces then before thei had bene, the experience wherof hath euer sythen (and now of late most of al) appered to the contrarie, for that thesaid wynes and woade, be daiely solde at suche excessiue prices, as hath not before bene sene within this Realme, and the nauie of the Realme therby ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the better mainteined.</p>
            <p>In consideracion wherof be it enacted, ordeined, and established by the Kyng our Souereigne Lorde, with thassent of the Lordes, and Commons in this present Parlament assembled, and by the aucthori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the same: That from the firste day of Februarie nexte commyng, after the Session of this present Parlament, vnto the first day of Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tober then folowyng, and so yerely, and from yere to yere, begynnyng at, and betwene the firste day of Februarie, and the firste daie of Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tober, it shall, and may be lawfull to all, and euery person, and persons beyng of the partes, or countries in amitie with our souereigne Lorde the Kyng, to conuey, or brynge in to this Realme, Irelande, Wales, Calais, or marches of the same, or Barwicke, any maner of wynes of the growyng of the Duchie of Guyen, or Gascoine, or of any other parte of Fraunce, and Tholouse woade, or any of them, in whatsoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer shippe, or shippes, crayer, or crayers, bote, or botes, or by any other meane, whosoeuer be, or shalbe therof owner, possessour, or proprieta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, beyng of the partes, or countries in amitie of our said Souereigne Lorde, or whosoeuer be therof Maister, or mariner, or mariners in the same, without any forfeicture, or penaltie thereof to be had. Thesaid Statute, or any thyng therin conteined to the contrarie in any wyse, notwithstandyng.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="19" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ The .xix. Chapiter. ❧ An Acte, touchyng the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaunge of Golde and Siluer.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here in the Parlament holden at Westmynster the .xxv. yere of the reigne of Kyng Edwarde the thirde, it was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded, that it should be lawful for euery mā to exchaunge Golde for Siluer, or Siluer for Golde, or for Golde and Siluer, so that no manne did holde the same as exchaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged,
<pb facs="tcp:150874:30"/> nor take no profite for makyng of suche exchaunge, vpon paine of forfeicture of the money so exchaunged, excepte the Kynges exchaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, whiche take profite of suche exchaunge, accordyng to an ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce before that tyme made. Whiche Statute notwithstandyng, diuers couetous persons of their owne aucthorities, haue of late taken vpon them to make exchaunges, aswel of coigned golde, as of coigned siluer, receiuyng and payeng therfore, more in value then hath bene de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared by the Kynges Proclamacion to be curraunt for, within this his Realme, and other his dominions, to the great hynderaunce of the commune wealth of this Realme.</p>
            <p>Be it therfore enacted by the Kyng our Souereigne Lorde by thas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent of the Lordes, and Commons in this present Parlament assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, and by thaucthoritie of the same, that if any person, or persones, after the firste day of Aprill nexte commyng, exchaunge any coigned Golde, coigned Siluer, or money, geuyng, receiuyng, or payeng any more in value, benefite, profite, or aduauntage for it, then the same is, or shalbe declared by the Kynges Maiesties Proclamacion to be currāt for, within this his highnes Realme, and other his dominions: That then al thesaid coigned Golde, Siluer, and money so exchaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, and euery parte, and parcel therof shalbe forfeicte, and the parties so offendyng, shal suffre imprisonement by the space of one whole yere, and make fyne at the Kynges pleasure. The one moietie of thesaid Golde, Siluer, or coigne so forfeicted to be to the Kyng our souereigne Lorde, and the other moietie to be to the partie that seaseth the same, or will sue for it by Bille, Plainte, Original, Action of debte, Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macion, or otherwyse in any of the Kynges Courtes of recorde, in whiche suite, no essoine, protection, or wager of lawe shall lye, be allo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed, or admitted.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="20" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ The .xx. Chapiter. ❧ An Acte against Vsurie.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HERE in the .xxxvij. yere of the reigne of the late Kyng of famous memorie Kyng Henry the eight, father to our Souereigne Lorde the Kyng, that no we is, amongest other Actes, and Statutes then made, it was enacted by aucthoritie of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lament, that no person, or persons, at any tyme af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre the last day of Ianuary in thesaid .xxxvij. yere, shoulde haue, receiue, accept, or take in lucre, or gaines, for the lone, forbearyng, or geuing day of paiment of any somme of monie, for one whole yere, aboue the somme of x. ł. in the C. and so aftre that rate, and not aboue, of, and for a more, or
<pb n="xxix" facs="tcp:150874:30"/> lesse some, or for a longer, or shorter tyme, vpon the paines and forfeic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, in thesaide acte mencioned and conteined. The whiche acte was not ment, or entended for the maitenaunce, and allowaunce of vsurie as diuers persones, blinded with inordinate loue of theymselues, haue and yet do mistake thesame, but rather was made &amp; intended, against all sortes, &amp; kyndes of vsury, as a thyng vnlawfull, as by the title and preamble of thesaide acte, it doeth plainly appere And yet neuertheles thesame was by thesaid acte permitted, for thauoidyng of a more euel and inconuenience, that before that time was vsed &amp; exercised. But for asmuche, as vsurie, is by the word of God, vtterly prohibited, as a vice most odious and detestable, as in diuers places of the holye scripture, it is euident to be sene, whiche thyng by no godly teachynges and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swasions can sinke into the hartes of diuers gredye, vncharitable, and couetous persones of thys realme, nor yet by any terrible threatnyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, of Goddes wrathe, and vengeaunce, that iustly hangeth ouer this realme, for the great and open vsury, therein dayly vsed and practised, they wil forsake suche filthy gaine, and lucre, oneles some temporal pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishement be prouided and ordeined in that behalfe. For reformation whereof, be it enacted by thaucthoritie of this present parlament, that from the first day of May, whiche shalbe in the yere of our Lorde God M. D. Lit. thesaide acte and statute, concernyng onely vsurye, lucre, or gaines, of, or for the lone, forbearyng, or geuing daies of any somme, or sommes of money, be vtterly abrogated, voyde, and repealed.</p>
            <p>And furthermore be it enacted by thaucthoritie aforesaid, that from and after thesaide firste day of Maie next commyng, no person, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons of what estate degre, qualitie, or condicion soeuer he, or thei be, by any corrupt, colourable, or deceiptful conueighaunce, sleight, or engine, or by any way, or meane, shal lend, geue, set out, deliuer, or forbeare a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny sōme, or sōmes of money, to any person or persones, or to any corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, or body politique, to, or for, any maner of vsurie, encrease, lucre, gain, or interest, to be had receiued, or hoped for, ouer &amp; aboue the sōme or sōmes so lent, geuen, sette oute, deliuered, or forborne, vpon paine of forfeiture the value, aswel of the sōme, or sōmes so lent, geuen, set out, deliuered, or forborne, as also of the vsurie, encrease, lucre, gaine, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest therof. And also vpon paine of imprisonment of the body, or bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, of euery such offendour, or offendours, and also to make fine, and raundsome, at the kynges wil and pleasure. The moitie of whiche for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feicture of thesaid value shalbe to the king, and the other moitie to the party that wil sue for thesame in any of the kynges courtes of recorde, by action of debt, bil, plaint, or information, wherin no wager of lawe, essome, or protection, shalbe allowed, or admitted.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="21" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ The .xxi. Chapiter. ¶ An acte against Tinckers and Pedlers.</head>
            <pb facs="tcp:150874:31"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Orasmuche, as it is euident, that Tinkers, Pedlers, and suche like vagraunt persones, are more hurtefull then necessary, to the common wealth of this realme. Be it therfore ordeined, established, &amp; enacted, by auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of this present Parlament, that from, &amp; after the feaste of the Natiuitie of S. Ihon Baptist nexte commyng, no persone, or persones, commonlye called Pedler, Tincker, or petie chapman, shal wander, or go, from one toune to another, or from place to place, out of the toune, parishe, or village, where suche persone shal dwell, and selle pinnes, pointes, laces, gloues kniues, glasses, tapes, or any suche kinde of wares, whatsoeuer, or ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cony skinnes, or suche like thyng, or vse, or exercise the trade, or oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupation of a Tincker, but onely suche persone, or persones, as shalbee thereunto licensed. And that in suche circuite, or compasse, as shalbe to hym, or theim, assigned by two Iustices of peace, or mo, of the Shiere where he, or they, shal dwell by writyng vnder their handes &amp; seales, vpon paine that euery persone whiche shall offend contrary to the mea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyng of this acte, shall by any Iustice of the Shiere where thesame of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence shalbe commited, vpon complaint and due proufe had, by witnes or otherwyse be imprisoned by the space of .xiiij. daies at the least.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="22" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ The .xxii. Chapitre. ¶ An acte for the puttyng doune of Gigge Milles.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Orasmuche, as true Drapery of Wollen Cothes is to be cōmended, aswel in forein realmes, as in thys realme of England, and al wayes and meanes, vsed to the contrary are to be eschued, and taken awaye: And forasmuche, as in many partes of this realme, is newly, and lately deuised, erected, builded, and v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, certaine Milles, called Gigge milles, for the per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chyng, and burlyng of clothe, by reason whereof, the true Draperie of this realme is wonderfully empaired, and the clothe thereof deceipt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully made, by reason of the vsyng of thesaide Gigge Milles: For re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy wherof, be it enacted by the Kyng our souereigne Lorde, the lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des spirituall and temporall, and the commons in thys present parla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mēt assembled, and by thaucthoritie of thesame, that no maner of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son or persons, aftre the last day of May next comming, shal vse, or oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupie, any of thesaide Gigge Milles, for the woorkyng of any Wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len Clothe, or Clothes, made, or to be made, within this Realme, v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon paine of forfeiture, for euery cloth so wrought, in, or by any of the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saide Milles, called Gigge Milles .v. ł. The moietie of all, and eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry suche forfeicture, and forfeictures, penaltie, and penalties, to be to the vse of our Souereigne Lorde the Kyng, and his heyres, and the
<pb n="xxx" facs="tcp:150874:31"/> other moietie, to the vse of hym that wil sue for the same in any of the Kynges Courtes, be it by writte, bille, plainte, or enformacion, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the defendaunt shal not be admitted to wage his lawe, nor any pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, essome, or Iniunction, shalbe to hym allowed.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="23" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ The .xxiij. Chapiter. ¶ An Acte for the true stuffyng of Fether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beddes, Mattresses, and quisshions</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>OR the auoidyng of the great deceipte vsed, and practised, in stuffyng of fetherbeddes, bolsters, pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, mattresses, quissheons, and quiltes,</p>
            <p>Be it enacted by the aucthoritie of this present Parlament, that from, and attre the laste day of Iune next commyng, no person, or persons, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer, shal make (to thentent to selle, or offre to be solde) any fetherbedde, bolstre, or pillowe, excepte the same be stuffed with drie pulled fethers, or cleane downe onely, without mynglyng of skalded fethers, fenne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>downe, thistledowne, sand, lyme, grauell, heare, or any other vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, or corrupte stuffe, vpon paine of forfeicture of al suche fetherbed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, bolsters, and pillowes, and euery of them so offred to be solde, or the value therof.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted by the same aucthoritie, that from, and aftre thesaid day, no person, or persons, shal make (to thentent to selle, or offre, or putte to sale) any quilte, mattresse, or quisshions, whiche shalbe stuffed with any other stuffe, then fethers, wolle, or flockes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, vpon paine of forfeicture, of al, and euery suche quiltes, mattres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, or quisshions, so solde, or offred to be solde, or the value therof. The moietie of all whiche forfeictures shalbe to the Kyng our souereigne Lorde, his heyres, and successours, and the other moietie therof to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny suche person, or persons, as will sue for the same in any of the Kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges Courtes of recorde, or in any other Courte, where in no wager of lawe, essoine, or protection shal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be allowed for the defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunt, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="24" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:150874:32"/>
            <head>¶ The .xxiiii. Chapiter. ¶ An Acte for the makyng of Hattes, Dorneckes, and Couerlectes, at Norwiche, and in the countie of Norff.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here the makyng of Hattes, Dorneckes, and Couer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectes, haue of late bene begonne to be practised with in the citie of Norwiche, in whiche citie there be good and profitable ordinaunces, and constitutions, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided, and ordeined for the preseruacion, and conti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nuance of the good makyng of the same hattes, dor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neckes, and couerlectes, by reason wherof the young and ydle people of thesaid citie, to a great nombre, haue bene and yet be well occupied, mainteined, and sette on worke. And forasmuche as di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers euell, and couetouse disposed persons, exercysyng the misteries of makyng of hattes, and weauyng of couerlectes, and dorneckes, within thesaid citie, and not beyng brought vp, or practised in thesaid Attes, or misteries, to thentent thei might occupie and exercise thesaid miste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries out of thesaid citie of Norwiche, where no suche ordinaunces and constituciōs be made, or prouided, haue withdrawen them selues from thesaid citie into certeine townes nighe about thesame citie, where thei do, and may occupie, and exercise the makyng of hattes, weauyng of couerlectes, and dorneckes, disceiptfully, and insufficiently, without controllement, to the vtter decaie, aswell of thesaid craftes, and miste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, as of thesaid citie, if remedie be not therin prouided:</p>
            <p>It may therfore be enacted by the Kynges Maiestie, with thassent of the Lordes Spiritual, and Temporal, and the commons in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent Parlament assembled, and by the aucthoritie of the same, that no person by hym selfe, or by his seruaunt, or apprentice, shall from, and aftre the feast of S. Michael Tharchaungel nexte commyng, make, or worke any feltes, or thrommed hattes, or weaue, or make any couerlec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, or dorneckes, or occupie, vse, or exercise the misteries, or occupaciōs of makyng of feltes, or thrōmed hattes, or weauyng of dorneckes, and couerlectes, or any of them, within thesaid citie of Norwiche, or within the countie of Norff, oneles he, or thei, that shal so make, or worke any such feltes, or hattes, or so occupie the occupaciō, or misterie of makyng of feltes, or hattes as aforesaid, within thesaid citie, or countie, be licē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, and admitted so to do by the Maiour, recorder, stewarde, and two iustices of the peace of thesaid citie, or by foure of thē, or that haue bene apprentice to the same occupacion, and misterie of feltes, and hattes makyng, by the space of .vij. yeres, &amp; in lyke case oneles suche person, or persons, that shal so make or weaue dorneckes, or so occupie the occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paciō, or misterie of dorneckes weauyng within thesaid citie, or countie be licenced, or admitted so to do by the Maiour, recorder, stewarde, and
<pb n="xxxi" facs="tcp:150874:32"/> two Iustices of the peace, of thesayde citie, or by foure of them, or that haue bene apprentice to thesayde misterie, and occupaciō, of dorneckes weauyng, by the terme of .vij. yeres: And onles he or they that shall so make, or weaue, couerlectes, or so occupie the attes or misterie of couer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lectes weauyng or makyng, be licenced and admitted so to doe, by the Maiour, Recorder, steward, &amp; two iustices of the peace, of thesaid citie. or by .iiij. of them, or that haue bene apprētice to the occupaciō, and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterie of couerlectes weauing &amp; makīg, by yē space or terme of .vij. yeres</p>
            <p>And be it also enacted by thaucthoritie aforesayde, that no persone, or persones, shal frō hencefurth make any feltes, or hattes, or weaue or make, any dorneckes, or couerlectes, as aforesaid, or occupie, exercise, or vse thoccupacion, artes, or misteries, of makyng of hattes, or feltes, or weauing or making of dorneckes, or couerlectes, or any of thē, as afore<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sayd, in any place, out of thesaid citie of Norwich, within thesaid coūtie of Norfolcke, but only in a corporate, or market toune, vpō pain of for feictyng, aswel of the feltes, hattes, dorneckes, and couerlectes, &amp; euery of them, whiche shalbe made, wrought, or wouē, contrary to the fourme effecte, and tenoure of this acte, or of any parte or clause thereof, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so ten shillinges, for euery haulf douseyne of thesayde feltes or hattes, and of iij. s̄ .iiij. ł. for euery couerlecte, and of .vi. s̄ .viij. ł. for euery .vi. yardes of dorneckes, so as is aforesaid, to be made, wouen or wrought contrary to this acte, the one haulf of whiche forfaictures, to be to the kyng our souereigne lorde, his heires, and successours, and the other haulfe therof to the persone, or persones, that shall or wil seyse thesame or that will or shall sue for thesame, or for any parte therof, in the kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges courte of the Guilde hall within thesaid citie of Norwiche, or in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other of the kynges courtes of recorde, within this Realme of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande, by Action of detinew, debte, playnt, byll, informacion, or other wise, in whiche sayd action or actions, sute, bill, plaint, or informacion, no essoyne, wager of lawe, protection or forein plea to the iurisdictiō of the court, shalbe admitted or allowed.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwaie, that all and euery suche persone and persones, as do nowe dwell or hereafter shall dwell, and exercise the mistery of dor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neckes, and couerlectes makyng, within the towne or paroche of Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, in thesayde countie of Norfolcke shall and may occupie, and exer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cise the makyng of dorneckes, and couerlectes, within thesayde towne of Pulham, as they haue heretofore vsed to do, any thyng in this acte conteined to the contrary, notwithstandyng.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted by the aucthoritie aforesayde, that if the Maiour, Recorder, Stewarde, or iustices of peace, of thesaide citie, for the tyme beyng, or any of them, shall take any somme of money or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde, for admittyng of any persone to occupie or vse any of the artes or misteries aforesayd, that for euery suche tyme, and euery suche case, the persone so offendyng, shall lose and forfeicte .v. ł. the one parte of
<pb facs="tcp:150874:33"/> whiche forfeicture to be to our souereigne lorde the kyng, and the other halfe to hym, or them that shall sue for thesame, as is aforesayde.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="25" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ The .xxv. Chapiter. ¶ An acte for kepers of Alehouses to be bounde by recognisaunce.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>OR as muche, as intollerable hurtes and troubles to the common wealth of this Realme dayly doe growe and encrease through suche abuses and disor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, as are had and vsed in commune Alehouses, and other houses called Tipling houses:</p>
            <p>It is therefore enacted by the Kynge our souere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>igne lorde, with thassent of the lordes, and commons in this present Parlament assembled, and by the aucthoritie of thesame that the Iustices of peace within euery shiere, Citie, Borough, toune corporate, fraunchesse, or libertie within this Realme, or two of them at the least (wherof one of theim to be of the <hi>Quorum)</hi> shal haue ful power and aucthoritie by vertue of this acte, within euery Shiere, Citie, Bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rough, Toune corporate, fraunchesse, and libertie, where they be Iusti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces of peace, to remoue, discharge, and putte away, commune selling of ale and Biere, in thesayde commune Alehouses and Tiplyng houses, in suche Toune, or Tounes, and places, where they shall thynke mete and cōuenient. And that none after the first day of May next cōmyng, shalbe admitted, or suffred to kepe any cōmune Ale house, or Tiplyng house, but suche as shalbe therunto admitted, and allowed in the open sessions of the peace, or els by two Iustices of the peace, whereof one to be of the <hi>Quorum.</hi> And that thesayde Iustices of the peace, or two of thē (whereof the one to be of the <hi>Quorum,)</hi> shall take bonde, and suretie, from tyme to tyme, by recognisaunce, of suche as shalbe admitted and allo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed hereafter to kepe any cōmune Alehouse, or Tiplyng house, aswell for, and against the vsyng of vnlaufull games, as also for the vsyng and maintenaunce of good ordre and rule to be had and vsed within thesame, as by their discretion shalbe thought necessary and conueniēt. For makyng of euery whiche recognisaunce, the partie or parties that shalbe so bounde, shall paie but .xij. d. And thesayde Iustices shal cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie thesame recognisaunce at the next quarter sessions of the peace, to be holden within thesame Shiere, Citie, Borough, Toune corporate, fraunchesse, or libertie, where suche Alehouse, or Tiplyng house shalbe. Thesame recognisaunce there to remaine of recorde before the Iusti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of peace of that Shiere, Citie, Borough, Toune corporate, fraun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chesse, or libertie vpon payne of forfeicture to the kyng for euery suche recognisaunce taken, and not certified .iij. ł .vi. s̄ .viij. d.</p>
            <p>And it is further enacted by thaucthoritie aforesaid, that the Iustices of peace of euery Shiere, citie, borough, toune corporate, fraunchesse, &amp;
<pb n="xxiij" facs="tcp:150874:33"/> libertie, where suche recognisaunce shalbe taken, shal haue power and aucthoritie by this acte, in their quarter Sessions of the peace, by pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sentment, informatiō, or otherwise by their discretion, to enquire of all suche persones, as shalbe admitted, and allowed, to kepe any Alehouse or Tiplyng house, and that be bounde by recognisaunce, as is aboue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saide, if they, or any of them, haue done any acte, or actes, wherby they or any of them haue forfeicted thesame recognisaunce. And thesaid Iu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>stices in euery shiere, and places where they be Iustices, shal vpon eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry suche presentmente, or enformation, awarde processe against euery suche persone, so presented, or complained vpon before theym, to shew why he shoulde not forfeit his recognisaunce, and shal haue ful power, and aucthoritie by this acte, to heare, and to determine thesame by all suche wayes and meanes, as by their discretion shalbe thought good.</p>
            <p>And it is further enacted by the aucthoritie aforesaide, that if anye persone, or persones, other then suche as shalbe herafter admitted and allowed by thesaide Iustices, shal aftre thesaide first day of May, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinatly, and vpon his owne aucthoritie, take vpon him, or them to ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe a commune alehouse, or tiplyng house, or shal contrarye to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundemēt of thesaid Iustices, or two of them, vse commonly selling of Ale, or biere, that then thesaid Iustices of peace, or .ii. of them (wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of, one to be of the <hi>Quorum)</hi> shal for euery suche offence, commit euery suche persone, or persones so offendyng, to the commune Gaole, within thesame Shiere, Citie, Borough, toune corporate, fraunchesse, or liber<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie, ther to remaine without baille or maiprise, by the space of .iij. daies And before his, or their deliueraunce, thesaide Iustices shall take reco<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>guisaunce for him, or them so committed, with two sureties that he, or they, shall not kepe any commune Ale house. Tipling house, or vse com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>munely sellyng of Ale, or Biere, as by the discretion of thesayde Iusti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces shalbe sene cōuenient. And thesaid Iustices shal make certificat of euery suche recognisaunce, and offence, at the nexte quarter Sessions that shalbe holden within thesame Shiere, Citie, Boroughe, Towne corporate, fraunchesse, or libertie, where thesame shalbe committed, or done. Whiche certificat shalbe a sufficient conuiction in the law, of the same offence. And thesayde Iustices of peace vpon thesaide certificat made, shall in open Sessions assesse the fine for euery suche offence, at twenty shyllynges.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwaie, that in suche townes and places, where any fayer or faiers shalbe kepte. that for the time only of thesame faier, or faiers it shalbe laufull for euery persone, and persones, to vse, commune sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng of Ale, or Biere in Bouthes, or other places there, for the relief of the Kynges Subiectes, that shall repaire to thesame, in suche like ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner, and sorte, as hath bene vsed, and done, in tymes passed. This acte, or any thyng therin conteined to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, notwithstandyng.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="26" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:150874:34"/>
            <head>¶ The .xxvi. Chapitre. ¶ An acte for writtes vpon proclamacions, and exigentes, to be currant within the countie Palantine of Lancastre.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here the Countie of Lancastre is, and of long tyme hath bene, one auncient Countie Palantine of it self in whiche Countie the kynges writte hathe not, nor yet doth not renne, so that the writte of proclamaciō awarded vpon any exigende, againste any persone, or persones, inhabityng within thesame countie, in any actiō wherin processe of outlawry doth lie, according to the statute made in the .vi. yere of the reigne of our late souereygne Lorde of famous memory, Kyng Henry the .viij. can not be directed to the Shierefe of thesayd countie Palantine, but vnto the Shierefe of the countie next adioynyng vnto thesayde countie Palantine, so that the partie dwellyng within thesaid countie Palantine, against whom any suche Exigende and Proclamation hath bene, or shalbe awarded, hath not had, nor herafter can haue, any knowlege of thesame sute, or processe, by reason wherof many persones inhabityng within thesaide countie Palantiue, without knowlege haue bene outlawed, and heraf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter be in lyke manner like to be outlawed, to their vtter vndoinges, if some spedy remedy be not the soner prouided.</p>
            <p>Be it therfore, and for diuers other good considerations enacted, or deined, and established, by the kyng our souereigne lord, with thassent of the lordes spiritual and temporal, and the commons in thys present parlament assembled, &amp; by thaucthoritie of thesame, that if, and when soeuer any writte of exigend, at any tyme aftre the first daye of Aprill next cōmyng, shalbe awarded at the sute of the king, his heires, or suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessours, kinges of this realme, or at y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> sute, or sutes of any other persō or persones, plaintiue, or plamtiues, in any action, or sute, in any of the courtes of our said souereigne lord the kyng, his heyres &amp; successours, kynges of this Realme, commonly called the kynges Benche, and the common place, againste any persone, or persones dwellyng within the said countie Palantine, that then ymmediatly vpon the awardyng of euery suche exigende, the Iustice, or Iustices before whome any suche writte of exigend vpon suche sute, or action shalbe sued, shall haue full power &amp; aucthoritie, by vertue of this acte, to award one writte of pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>clamation, accordyng to the tenour and effect of writtes of proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion awarded vpon exigentes, and cōmonly directed oute of any of the sayde courtes into London, or into any other Shieres of this Realme against any person, or persons, dwellyng in other Shiere, or Shieres of this realme where the kinges writte doth renne, according to the or<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der and fourme of thesaid statute, made in the sixth yeare of the reigne
<pb n="xxxiij" facs="tcp:150874:34"/> of thesaid late kyng to be directed to the shierefe of thesaid county pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantine of Lancastre, where it shal happen thesaid defendaunt against whome any suche action shalbe sued, as is aforesaide, to be dwellyng &amp; not to the Shierefe of any other Shiere nexte adioynyng to thesaide countie palātine, any law, custome, or vsage hertofore vsed to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary notwithstanding. And that euery suche writte of proclamation so to be hereafter awarded to the Shierefe of thesaid countie palātine shal haue thesame teste and daie of retourne, as the exigendes wheru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon euery suche writte of Proclamation shalbe awarded, shall haue. And that euery suche shierefe of the saide Countie Palantine of Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>castre, to whome any such writte, and writtes of proclamation shalbe directed, shal make Proclamations of thesaide writte, and writtes of proclamation, accordyng to the tenour of thesame, and shal make true returnes of thesame, in suche courte, and courtes, and before suche Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stices as the tenour of thesame writte, and writtes of proclamations, shal require, and demaunde. And that all outlawries hereafter to bee promulged, or pronounced against any persone, or persones, vpon any suche exigend, or exigendes awarded against any persone, or persones dwellyng in the saide countie Palantine of Lancastre, and no writte of Proclamations awarded in fourme abouesaide, to the Shierefe of thesaid countie Palantine of Lancastre, where the partie defendaunt shalbe as is aforesaide dwellyng, or not returned, to bee clerely voyde, and of none effect nor force in the law.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted by thaucthoritie aforesaid, that euery shie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>refe of thesaide countie Palantine for the tyme beyng, shal haue in eue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry of thesaide courtes of the kynges bēche, &amp; of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> cōmon place, one suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient deputy at the least, to receiue al such writtes of proclamations, whiche shalbe hereafter directed, to euerye suche Shierefe of the saide county palātine, for whom thesame deputie, or deputies shalbe apoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, in lyke maner and fourme, and vpon lyke paynes, as by the former statutes and lawes of this Realme, other Shierefes of other shieres, or counties within this realme of Englande, be bounden to haue in ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of thesame courtes. And that al suche writtes of proclamations aforesaid, shalbe deliuered vnto euery suche deputie, or deputies, of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde, in thesame courtes, &amp; either of them, &amp; also lyke fees shalbe paid for making euerye suche writtes of Proclamations, and for enrollyng thesame of record, as is limited in thesame statute, made in thesaid .vi. yere of our saide late souereigne lorde kyng Henry the .viii.</p>
            <p>Be it further enacted, and established by the aucthoritie aforesaide, that if any suche writte, or writtes of proclamations, hereafter to be di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rected to any Shierefe of thesaid coūty Palantine of Lancastre, be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered vnto any of the shierefes of thesaid coūtie palātine for the time being, or to his, or their deputie, or deputies, in maner &amp; fourme afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said, &amp; thesame shierefe, or shierefes, do not make true returne of euery
<pb facs="tcp:150874:35"/> suche writte, and writtes, of proclamations into suche court, and cour<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes, out of which thesaid writte or writtes of proclamations, shalbe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded, that for euery suche defaulte of non retourne, euery such She<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>refe for the tyme beyng, shal lose, and forfaicte .v. ł. the one half where of shalbe to our souereigne lord the kyng, his heyres, and successours, &amp; the other haulf therof, to any suche persone, or persones, as wil sue for thesame, in one action of debt to be grounded vpon this acte, in any of the kynges courtes of Recorde, wherin none essoine, protection, or wa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ger of lawe shalbe allowed, or admitted.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwayes, that this acte, or any thyng therin conteined, shall not in any wyse extende, or be preiudicial to thesame county Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantine of Lancastre, for, or concernyng such liberties, fraunchesses, or priuileges, as belong to thesame, or to any ministres, or officers of the same county Palantine otherwyse, or in any other maner then by the true meanyng of thys acte is before prouided and declared, any thyng in this acte mencioned to the contrary notwithstandyng.</p>
            <p>Prouided also, and be it further enacted and established, by the auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie aforesaid, that if any person, or persones, dwellyng within the sayd countie Palantine, aftre the aforesaide firste day of Aprill, shalbe outlawed, in any such sute, or action, as is aforesaid, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> then al writtes of special <hi>Capias utlegatum,</hi> single <hi>capias utlegatum, non molestandum</hi> &amp; al other processe, for, or against any person, or persones, so outlawed, shal and may, from thencefurthe be directed, from tyme to tyme, to the Chauncellour of the Duchie of Lancastre, who shall make lyke writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes and proces thereupon, and of lyke effect, sealed with the seale of thesaid county Palantine of Lancastre, to be directed to the Sherefe of thesaid countie Palantine, for the time beyng as heretofore hath bene vsed, and accustomed in suche cases.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>RICHARDVS GRAFTON typographus Regius excude: bat. Mense Aprili. 1552.</p>
            <p>Cum priuilegio ad imprimendum solum.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:150874:35"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>